<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Jake McCrary's articles on books]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-13T02:16:33+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/reading-in-2024/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/reading-in-2024/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2024]]></title>
    <updated>2025-02-13T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year, I take the time to update my records of what I've read the previous year and write up a summary.</p><p>Previous summaries: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>, <a href='/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/'>2019</a>, <a href='/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/'>2020</a>, <a href='/blog/2022/01/02/reading-in-2021/'>2021</a>, <a href='/blog/2023/01/14/reading-in-2022/'>2022</a>, <a href='/blog/2024/02/18/reading-in-2023/'>2024</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010.</p><h2>2024 Goals</h2><blockquote><p> I'd like to maintain a regular reading practice.  I think this means having a similar number of pages read this year. </p></blockquote><p>Ehh, I don't think I succeeded in this goal, despite not being too far off the number of pages I read in 2023.</p><blockquote><p> I have a massive stack of books at home that I haven't read through yet, I'd like to whittle that down some. </p></blockquote><p>I'm pretty sure there is a universal law that a stack of unread books can only grow and my coffee table is proof it is true.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Below are the highlights from 2024. Any title link will bring you to Goodreads.</p><h3>Five-star books</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/158875813-prophet-song'>Prophet Song</a> by Paul Lynch</h4><p>This book was beautiful. I cried. The writing is lyrical, the subject matter is tough, and you'll probably tear up too.</p><p>You may have heard that reading fiction can help you be more empathetic. I could feel this book do that to me.</p><p>Go read it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/197828937-all-fours'>All Fours</a> by Miranda July</h4><p>This book is fantastic. I literally laughed out loud multiple times. Miranda July's writing tickles me in just the right way.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/145625425-day'>Day</a> by Michael Cunningham</h4><p>I guess I haven't gotten sick of books that deal with the COVID-19 pandemic. Maybe that is because I've only read stories on the topic from really solid authors.</p><p>This book gives you a glimpse into the lives of a family on three different days (April 5 2019, 2020 and 2021). It has been nearly a year since I've read this and unfortunately I don't remember what I enjoyed so much about this book.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6567453-looking-for-alaska'>Looking for Alaska</a> by John Green</h4><p>I don't know, sometimes you read a young adult book and it just makes an impact. I doubt others will enjoy this as much as I did at the time I read it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/157998171-supercommunicators'>Supercommunicators</a> by Charles Duhigg</h4><p>I'm projecting but I'd guess that most folks would be better off if they became better communicators. And that is exactly what this book says it will do.</p><p>I enjoyed reading this and will benefit by going back through and trying to apply the lessons found in this book.</p><h3>Other highlights</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/91288912-the-zen-of-climbing'>The Zen of Climbing</a> by Francis Sanzaro</h4><p>Some parts were great; some parts were so-so. Seeing Zen principles applied to climbing was thought-provoking.</p><h4>Ada Palmer's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/166200-terra-ignota'>Terra Ignota</a> series</h4><p>The right reader will absolutely love this series. Unfortunately, I'm not that reader. Still, I enjoyed the series quite a bit. The world built by Ada Palmer is fascinating. I'll admit though, I think about this world quite often. This book made an impact.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59016923-small-things-like-these'>Small Things Like These</a> by Claire Keegan</h4><p>A short and powerful book.</p><h4>Jasper Fforde's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/51553-shades-of-grey'>Shades of Grey</a> series</h4><p>At the time of writing this, I think there are only two books in the series and those are the two that I've read.</p><p>This series puts you into a world of rules and structure, with society being built on top of hierarchies based on how much color you can see. It is an interesting coming of age story as the main character learns to navigate this world. This is a fun and interesting world and I hope more books come out in the series.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/204193039-i-m-starting-to-worry-about-this-black-box-of-doom'>I'm Starting to Worry About This Black Box of Doom</a> by Jason Pargin</h4><p>This book calls out our modern world and our addiction to outrage-as-entertainment, addiction to screens, and the information bubbles we live in.</p><p>I really enjoyed all of that. In a way, this book takes non-fiction books, such as Hans Rosling's Factfulness (a book about how much better the world has become) and books on social media, filter bubbles, and polarization, and packages it up into a fiction tale demonstrating how it the Internet warps how we perceive each other and our modern world. Some readers might not enjoy characters going on rants and arguments about these topics but I really enjoyed it.</p><p>This book is a good reminder that we're really more similar than we are different and that modern media (social, news, etc) really divides us and both makes the world seem worse and actually be worse.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/204079049-rejection'>Rejection</a> by Tony Tulathimutte</h4><p>A collection of stories about rejection that are loosely connected. It is fun satire. I probably could have given this one five stars.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>I read 35 books in 2024.</p><pre><code class="language-org">| Year | # of Pages | # of Books |
|------+------------+------------|
| 2024 |      12919 |         37 |
| 2023 |      14956 |         53 |
| 2022 |      10127 |         35 |
| 2021 |      19564 |         57 |
| 2020 |      12093 |         43 |
| 2019 |      15994 |         42 |
| 2018 |      13538 |         36 |
| 2017 |      18317 |         48 |
| 2016 |      22790 |         59 |
| 2015 |      21689 |         51 |
| 2014 |      24340 |         71 |
| 2013 |      19815 |         60 |
| 2012 |      14208 |         44 |
| 2011 |       9179 |         19 |
| 2010 |      14667 |         46 |
</code></pre><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2024.svg" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books and pages for each month" /></p><p>Electronic books continue to dominate.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|           | 2024 | 2023 | 2022 | 2021 | 2020 | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------|
| audiobook |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |
| ebook     |   35 |   51 |   34 |   56 |   41 |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    1 |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    1 |    2 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>I did not read many non-fiction books last year.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|                           |   2024 |  2023 | 2022 |   2021 |   2020 |   2019 |   2018 |
|---------------------------+--------+-------+------+--------+--------+--------+--------|
| fiction                   |     33 |    47 |   28 |     46 |     26 |     28 |     29 |
| non-fiction               |      4 |     6 |    7 |     11 |     17 |     23 |     14 |
| fiction:non-fiction ratio | 8.25:1 | 7.8:1 |  4:1 | 4.18:1 | 1.53:1 | 1.22:1 | 2.07:1 |

</code></pre><p>Here is the star rating distribution.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|             | 3 stars | 4 stars | 5 stars |
|-------------+---------+---------+---------|
| fiction     |      17 |      12 |       4 |
| non-fiction |       1 |       2 |       1 |
</code></pre><h2>2025 goals</h2><p>For the last month or so, I've been better about reading with a regular cadence. I'd like to keep that up.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2024/02/18/reading-in-2023/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2024/02/18/reading-in-2023/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2023]]></title>
    <updated>2024-02-18T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year (not so much the beginning this year), I take the time to update my records of what I've read the previous year and write up a summary.</p><p>Previous summaries: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>, <a href='/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/'>2019</a>, <a href='/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/'>2020</a>, <a href='/blog/2022/01/02/reading-in-2021/'>2021</a>, <a href='/blog/2023/01/14/reading-in-2022/'>2022</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010.</p><h2>2023 Goals</h2><p>Last year I wrote: </p><blockquote><p> I’d like to do a better job of keeping track of my reading. This should be pretty easy to do. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> I don’t feel too bad about the reduction in reading but I’d like to read more this year. Some of my reading time has been replaced with worthwhile endeavors but not always. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> Reading rejuvenates me. I need to keep it a regular part of my life. </p></blockquote><p>Well, I don't remember how poorly I did in 2022 of keeping tack of reading but I don't think I did a great job in 2023. Was it better than 2022?  Perhaps.</p><p>I didn't write many reviews for specific books nor did I send out any emails about what I was reading throughout the year. But I did do fewer corrections of the data I had in Goodreads.</p><p>I did read more than I did last year.</p><p>If I were grading myself on how well I achieved my goal, I'd give myself a B.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Below are the highlights from 2023. Any title link will bring you to Goodreads.</p><h3>Five-star books</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58601245-sea-of-tranquility'>Sea of Tranquility</a> by Emily St. John Mandel</h4><p>I started off the year with this book and really enjoyed it. It is a pandemic story that has characters spanning hundreds of years.</p><p>It is a little weird and beautiful. It did an excellent job of conveying feeling.</p><p>This is one of the few books that I did a mini-review of when I finished it. That review: </p><blockquote><p> A beautiful novel. While reading, I found myself rereading parts. Not because the sentences were confusing but because they expressed such a clear feeling. </p></blockquote><p>I highly recommend this book.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/53440834-the-first-bad-man'>The First Bad Man</a> by Miranda July</h4><p>This book is real weird and fantastic. The main character is extremely interesting. I had a blast reading this.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52381770-network-effect'>Network Effect</a> by Martha Wells</h4><p>I really enjoy this series and thought this as an excellent addition to it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58916147-tomorrow-and-tomorrow-and-tomorrow'>Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow</a> by Gabrielle Zevin</h4><p>This was an excellent book about friendship and creative, collaborative pursuits.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61351606-how-to-live'>How to Live: 27 conflicting answers and one weird conclusion</a> by Derek Sivers</h4><p>A friend offered to send copies of this books to anyone who was up to reading it and I'm glad I spoke up and asked. Each chapter presents a philosophy. And the next chapter usually presents a different, conflicting philosophy. Every chapter is small, so it is easy to read a bit and take some time to reflect.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18652778-the-little-book-of-talent'>The Little Book of Talent: 52 Tips for Improving Your Skills</a> by Daniel Coyle</h4><p>A bunch of distilled ideas around improvement. No fluff, just tips.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13453029-wool-omnibus'>Wool Omnibus</a> by Hugh Howey</h4><p>I have mixed feelings about including this book on the list. I reread this series when I was debating watching the television show. Even on a second read, I still enjoyed this story.</p><p>Is it complex and view shattering science fiction? Nahh, not really.</p><p>Is it entertaining? Yep.</p><h3>Other highlights</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61618096-chain-gang-all-stars'>Chain-Gang All-Stars</a> by Nana Kwame Adjei-Brenyah</h4><p>This is a really well done book that explores a modern gladiator system of punishment for criminals. It is dark and creative and a solid commentary on modern society.</p><p>Maybe this should have been five-stars.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35162756-the-sparrow'>The Sparrow</a> by Mary Doria Russell</h4><p>I knew nothing about it going in and thought this was a interesting take on first contact with aliens.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>I read 53 books in 2023.</p><pre><code class="language-org">| Year | # of Pages | # of Books |
|------+------------+------------|
| 2023 |      14956 |         53 |
| 2022 |      10127 |         35 |
| 2021 |      19564 |         57 |
| 2020 |      12093 |         43 |
| 2019 |      15994 |         42 |
| 2018 |      13538 |         36 |
| 2017 |      18317 |         48 |
| 2016 |      22790 |         59 |
| 2015 |      21689 |         51 |
| 2014 |      24340 |         71 |
| 2013 |      19815 |         60 |
| 2012 |      14208 |         44 |
| 2011 |       9179 |         19 |
| 2010 |      14667 |         46 |
</code></pre><p>There are definitely some spiky months in the data.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2023.svg" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books and pages for each month" /></p><p>Unsurprisingly, electronic books are still the dominate format.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|           | 2023 | 2022 | 2021 | 2020 | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------|
| audiobook |    0 |    0 |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |
| ebook     |   51 |   34 |   56 |   41 |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    2 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>Fiction continued to dominate the book count this year. If I did this by page count I think it would tell a different story, as I read quite a few short stories published as Kindle books and this skewed my fiction book count high.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|                           |  2023 | 2022 |   2021 |   2020 |   2019 |   2018 |
|---------------------------+-------+------+--------+--------+--------+--------|
| fiction                   |    47 |   28 |     46 |     26 |     28 |     29 |
| non-fiction               |     6 |    7 |     11 |     17 |     23 |     14 |
| fiction:non-fiction ratio | 7.8:1 |  4:1 | 4.18:1 | 1.53:1 | 1.22:1 | 2.07:1 |

</code></pre><p>Here is the star rating distribution.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|             | 2 stars | 3 stars | 4 stars | 5 stars |
|-------------+---------+---------+---------+---------|
| fiction     |       0 |      21 |      22 |       4 |
| non-fiction |       0 |       1 |       3 |       2 |
</code></pre><h2>2024 goals</h2><p>I'd like to maintain a regular reading practice. I think this means having a similar number of pages read this year.</p><p>I have a massive stack of books at home that I haven't read through yet, I'd like to whittle that down some.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2023/01/14/reading-in-2022/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2023/01/14/reading-in-2022/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2022]]></title>
    <updated>2023-01-14T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year, I look back at my records and reflect on the books I read the previous year.</p><p>Previous years: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>, <a href='/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/'>2019</a>, <a href='/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/'>2020</a>, <a href='/blog/2022/01/02/reading-in-2021/'>2021</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010.</p><p>This year I did a poor job of keeping Goodreads updated. I had somewhat stopped updating Goodreads, or at least caring if I did it accurately, because I thought they were killing the ability to export your data. Luckily, that feature hasn't been removed so I'm going to continue using the service.</p><h2>2022 goals</h2><p>Last year I wrote:</p><blockquote><p> I used to be pretty good at capturing some thoughts upon completion of a book.  I haven't been doing a great job of that.  I'd like to do better this year. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> We'll see what that entails but it might take the form of having more discipline around sending out some thoughts in the <a href='{{' title=site.subscribe_email }}>newsletter</a>. </p></blockquote><p>I accomplished absolutely nothing related to the goals I wrote at the beginning of 2022.</p><p>I didn't write down thoughts on books closer to when I finished them. I didn't keep my Goodreads data updated. I didn't send out updates to my newsletter.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Below are some highlights from 2022. The titles link to Goodreads.</p><p>I didn't write many reviews on Goodreads this year and did not write detailed reviews in this article. I'd encourage you to click the links and read reviews on Goodreads.</p><h3>Five-star books</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61033655-liberation-day'>Liberation Day: Stories</a> by George Saunders</h4><p>I love George Saunders' writing and especially enjoy his short stories. This collection delivered.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/53513520-the-lathe-of-heaven'>The Lathe of Heaven</a> by Ursula K. Le Guin</h4><p>A science fiction classic that deserves to be read.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55742688-four-thousand-weeks'>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</a> by Oliver Burkeman</h4><p>Gist of the book: Life is short and you won't be able to accomplish everything you desire.</p><p>I enjoyed reading this and would benefit from reading it (or at least the Goodread's reviews) again. This <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4224854256?book_show_action=true'>review</a> on Goodreads is excellent.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51202930-breath'>Breath: The New Science of a Lost Art</a> by James Nestor</h4><p>I found this book fascinating and it made me interested in breathing. It was a nice mix of self-experimentation and reporting on studies. The history of the shape of our faces and how it affects breathing really hooked me into this book.</p><p>I enjoyed the book enough that I also listened to a significant portion of it while on a road trip so my partner could also consume it.</p><h3>Other Highlights</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61741867-mount-chicago'>Mount Chicago: A Novel</a> by Adam Levin</h4><p>This probably could have been rated five stars. It is a ridiculous and long novel that rewards the reader for paying attention.</p><p>Probably the highlights for me were the chapters from the perspective of a pet.</p><p>I thought a couple sections dragged a bit and are what held me back from five stars.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/60387334-novelist-as-a-vocation'>Novelist as a Vocation</a> by Haruki Murakami</h4><p>To say I like Murakami's writing would be an understatement, so reading a collection of essays by him about his writing was a pleasure. I learned a bunch about Murakami and his journey to becoming an internationally renowned author. At least as presented by Murakami, aspects of his life seem as surreal as some of his books.</p><p>This didn't earn five stars because I found myself just not caring about some of the topics. But overall, solid book, especially for someone that enjoys Murakami and enjoys reading about writing.</p><h3>Octavia Butler's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/55489-patternmaster'>Patternmaster</a> series.</h3><p>Octavia Butler is one of my favorite authors and I devoured the first three books in this series. I enjoyed the first book, Wild Seed, the best.</p><p>I didn't realize until writing this up that there is a fourth book in the series and I've immediately queued up reading it.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>Compared to my usual number of books and pages read, this was a low reading year. I read 35 books in 2022.</p><pre><code class="language-org">| Year | # of Pages | # of Books |
|------+------------+------------|
| 2022 |      10127 |         35 |
| 2021 |      19564 |         57 |
| 2020 |      12093 |         43 |
| 2019 |      15994 |         42 |
| 2018 |      13538 |         36 |
| 2017 |      18317 |         48 |
| 2016 |      22790 |         59 |
| 2015 |      21689 |         51 |
| 2014 |      24340 |         71 |
| 2013 |      19815 |         60 |
| 2012 |      14208 |         44 |
| 2011 |       9179 |         19 |
| 2010 |      14667 |         46 |
</code></pre><p>Here is a breakdown of books finished by month. There were even a couple months where I allegedly didn't finish a single book, though I wonder if that is actually true or of it is a data issue.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2022.svg" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books and pages for each month" /></p><p>Electronic books continue to be the dominant format. Audio book could be 0.5 for how much I listened to Breath while on a road trip.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|           | 2022 | 2021 | 2020 | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------|
| audiobook |    0 |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |
| ebook     |   34 |   56 |   41 |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    1 |    0 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>Fiction dominated this year.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|                           | 2022 |   2021 |   2020 |   2019 |   2018 |
|---------------------------+------+--------+--------+--------+--------|
| fiction                   |   28 |     46 |     26 |     28 |     29 |
| non-fiction               |    7 |     11 |     17 |     23 |     14 |
| fiction:non-fiction ratio |  4:1 | 4.18:1 | 1.53:1 | 1.22:1 | 2.07:1 |

</code></pre><p>Here is the star rating distribution.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|             | 2 stars | 3 stars | 4 stars | 5 stars |
|-------------+---------+---------+---------+---------|
| fiction     |       2 |      10 |      14 |       2 |
| non-fiction |       0 |       0 |       5 |       2 |
</code></pre><h2>2023 goals</h2><p>I'd like to do a better job of keeping track of my reading. This should be pretty easy to do.</p><p>I don't feel too bad about the reduction in reading but I'd like to read more this year. Some of my reading time has been replaced with worthwhile endeavors but not always.</p><p>Reading rejuvenates me. I need to keep it a regular part of my life.</p><p>Have any book recommendations? Please shoot me an email or leave a comment.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2022/01/02/reading-in-2021/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2022/01/02/reading-in-2021/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2021]]></title>
    <updated>2022-01-02T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year, I reflect on books I've read in the previous year. I take a look at my records, fix errors, and think about reading goals for the upcoming year.</p><p>Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>, <a href='/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/'>2019</a>, and <a href='/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/'>2020</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?shelf=read_2021'>Here</a> is my 2021.</p><h2>2021 Goals</h2><p>Last year I wrote:</p><blockquote><p> I have quite a few unread books sitting on my virtual and physical bookshelf.  This feels like setting a really low-bar but this year I'd like to read some of these unread-but-owned books. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> I'm also planning on reading at least one book on writing and one book on climbing.<br /> This goal is almost a subset of the above goal as I have books on both these topics sitting on my shelf. </p></blockquote><p>Did I achieve those goals? No.</p><p>Looking through my list of read books, I think only one of those a book I owned at the beginning of 2021. I did not read <i>some</i> already owned books; I read a single already owned book.</p><p>I did read a book on writing, George Saunders' <i>A Swim in a Pond in the Rain</i>, and multiple climbing books, <i>Rock Climbing Technique</i> by John Kettle and <i><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57691814-rock-climbing-in-kentucky-s-red-river-gorge'>Rock Climbing in Kentucky's Red River Gorge</a></i> by James Maples.</p><p>Early in 2020, at the request of some readers of this site, I started a <a href='{{' title=site.subscribe_email }}>mailing list</a>. During 2020 I used this newsletter as a way to notify subscribers of new articles posted to this website and write up short blurbs on books I had finished. Except for a single email, I also didn't send out any updates to the newsletter.</p><p>This is partially because I didn't write many articles last year. I generally try to write about one article a month but I did not do that in 2021. We'll see if I pick back up this habit in 2022.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Below are some highlights from 2021. The titles link to Goodreads.</p><p>I didn't write many reviews on Goodreads this year and did not write detailed reviews in this article. I'd encourage you to click the links and read reviews on Goodreads.</p><h3>Five-star books</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/44767458-dune'>Dune</a> by Frank Herbert</h4><p>This was my third time reading Dune. I read it in preparation for seeing the 2021 film.</p><p>I'm a huge fan of Dune but parts of it definitely haven't aged well. I think the story manages to be complex and have plenty of movement but somehow isn't overwhelming. I thought the film did a pretty good job of capturing that.</p><p>The first time I read Dune, I also made the very first <a href='https://jakemcc.gumroad.com/l/dune-dictionary'>Kindle Dune Dictionary</a>. If you are reading on a Kindle and haven't read the book before, I'd recommend purchasing the dictionary. I didn't find it useful  on my third time through the book but it made my first read through better.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12621704-memory'>Memory</a> by Lois McMaster Bujold</h4><p>In August and September, I pretty much devoured the entire <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/98250-vorkosigan-saga-publication-order'>Vorkosigan Saga</a>. I read all these books pretty much back to back and can barely distinguish them.</p><p>I'd recommend the series. It was a fun series and there are quite a few books in it. For some reason, this book stood out and is the only one I gave five stars.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/39873472-a-memory-called-empire'>A Memory Called Empire</a> and <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/45154547-a-desolation-called-peace'>A Desolation Called Peace</a> by Arkady Martine</h4><p>These are two incredible books. Arkady Martine built a great world. Politics, aliens, and poetry all show up in these books and it is great.</p><p>Go read some reviews (perhaps <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2754542016?book_show_action=true'>this</a> and <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3361651782?book_show_action=true'>this</a>) and then go start this series.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36075657-the-overstory'>The Overstory</a> by Richard Powers</h4><p>The book starts with what feels like a collection of short stories and grows into a story of struggle, triumph, and failure. I can't point to what made this book stand out to me but a I really enjoyed it. It might have had some moments that dragged a bit but I still loved it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55710260-this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war'>This Is How You Lose the Time War</a> by Amal El-Mohtar</h4><p>I went into this book knowing nothing about it and found it beautiful. The writing is lyrical and the way the story is told worked really well.</p><p>The book isn't that long and I absolutely devoured it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55612579-zikora'>Zikora</a> by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</h4><p>This is a 35 page short story. Go spend the short time it takes to read it. And then go read the rest of Adichie's writing.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/53487237-a-swim-in-a-pond-in-the-rain'>A Swim in a Pond in the Rain: In Which Four Russians Give a Master Class on Writing, Reading, and Life</a> by George Saunders</h4><p>This book is fantastic. Generally, the format of the book is that you read a short story and then read George Saunders' thoughts about that story.</p><p>This book slightly changed how I think about stories.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19635587-dept-of-speculation'>Dept. of Speculation</a> by Jenny Offill</h4><p>This is a relatively short, beautiful book. I experienced a full range of emotions while reading it.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55614248-think-again'>Think Again: The Power of Knowing What You Don't Know</a> by Adam M. Grant</h4><p>A solid book on the benefits of rethinking your positions. A very short summary is that it is good to update your beliefs and be curious. There is little benefit to being wrong longer. Learn how to rejoice in correcting your beliefs and embrace updating your viewpoints.</p><p>There is a some overlap of concepts in this book and the book Moral Tribes. If you are also well-versed in cognitive biases, parts of this book will be a repeat.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/32605769-the-devops-handbook'>The DevOps Handbook: How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, and Security in Technology Organizations</a> by Gene Kim</h4><p>I think a second edition came out immediately after I finished reading the first edition. Hopefully the second edition has high quality updates as the original edition of this book is pretty solid. I've lived the vision promoted by this book and it is a good place to be.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40526042-rock-climbing-technique'>Rock Climbing Technique: The Practical Guide to Movement Mastery</a> by John Kettle</h4><p>A short book full of specific drills that are intended to improve your skill in climbing. This book isn't about improving your strength, flexibility, or endurance. It is all about getting better at movement and paying attention to your movement patterns.</p><p>I've taken some of these drills and incorporated them into my climbing practice. I plan on digging back into this book and incorporating more of them.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54965614-drug-use-for-grown-ups'>Drug Use for Grown-Ups: Chasing Liberty in the Land of Fear</a> by Carl L. Hart</h4><p>This book is a mix of the author's personal experience, policy, and science and makes the argument that drugs should be legal. Probably worth reading if you have any sort of reaction to that last sentence.</p><p>Reading some reviews on Goodreads gives a fairly balanced view of what this book is about. Even if I personally gave this book five stars, I find myself agreeing with a wide range of reviews by others.</p><h3>Other Highlights</h3><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40864002-a-psalm-for-the-wild-built'>A Psalm for the Wild-Built</a> by Becky Chambers</h4><p>A couple other reviews (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3567191782?book_show_action=true'>one</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3762535675?book_show_action=true'>two</a>) described this book as comforting science fiction. I think that is a great description.</p><p>The world feels cozy. It is full of generally nice folks going about their lives and interacting with each other over tea. This main character in this book is non-binary and you get to hang out with them as they live their life. It feels like a nice place to be with reasonable folks and respect between humans, nature, and robots.</p><p>It is a relaxing read that feels like a gentle fable that muses on life and what it means to exist.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57691814-rock-climbing-in-kentucky-s-red-river-gorge'>Rock Climbing in Kentucky's Red River Gorge</a> by James Maples</h4><p>This book has a very narrow audience. If you have heard about the Red River Gorge, rock climb, and are interested in the history of the area you should read this book.</p><p>I learned a lot about one of my favorite places to rock climb.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/56247202-crossroads'>Crossroads</a> by Jonathan Franzen</h4><p>There is a really good chance I should have given this book five stars. It was great. This book tells the story of the Hildebrandt family through interweaving perspectives of the family's members. The characters are complex and the perspectives are interesting. I hope Franzen can continue to deliver this level of story in the sequels.</p><p>This <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4264230041?book_show_action=true'>goodreads review</a> does a great job of selling the book.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/38466356-the-art-of-gathering'>The Art of Gathering</a> by Priya Parker</h4><p>This book does a wonderful job of describing what makes a gathering great. It was a bit hopeful to read this book early in 2021.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/32758901-all-systems-red'>All Systems Red</a> by Martha Wells</h4><p>A fun novella told from the perspective of an android.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54250259-klara-and-the-sun'>Klara and the Sun</a> by Kazuo Ishiguro</h4><p>This book was beautiful. It manages to feel slightly off and this is completely appropriate given the narrator. This leads to some really amusing bits of writing.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>I thought I had read less this year than I had in recent years but I was wrong. I read 57 books and 19,564 pages in 2021.</p><pre><code class="language-org">| Year | # of Pages | # of Books |
|------+------------+------------|
| 2021 |      19564 |         57 |
| 2020 |      12093 |         43 |
| 2019 |      15994 |         42 |
| 2018 |      13538 |         36 |
| 2017 |      18317 |         48 |
| 2016 |      22790 |         59 |
| 2015 |      21689 |         51 |
| 2014 |      24340 |         71 |
| 2013 |      19815 |         60 |
| 2012 |      14208 |         44 |
| 2011 |       9179 |         19 |
| 2010 |      14667 |         46 |
</code></pre><p>Here is a breakdown of books finished by month. I can tell from looking at August and September that I started and finished the Vorkosigan series during those months.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2021.png" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books and pages for each month" /></p><p>Electronic books continue to be the dominant format.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|           | 2021 | 2020 | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------+------+------|
| audiobook |    0 |    1 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |
| ebook     |   56 |   41 |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    0 |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    1 |    1 |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>Fiction dominated this year.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|                           |   2021 |   2020 |   2019 |   2018 |
|---------------------------+--------+--------+--------+--------|
| fiction                   |     46 |     26 |     28 |     29 |
| non-fiction               |     11 |     17 |     23 |     14 |
| fiction:non-fiction ratio | 4.18:1 | 1.53:1 | 1.22:1 | 2.07:1 |

</code></pre><p>Here is the star rating distribution.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|             | 2 stars | 3 stars | 4 stars | 5 stars |
|-------------+---------+---------+---------+---------|
| fiction     |       2 |      17 |      19 |       8 |
| non-fiction |       1 |       2 |       3 |       5 |
</code></pre><h2>2022 goals</h2><p>I used to be pretty good at capturing some thoughts upon completion of a book. I haven't been doing a great job of that. I'd like to do better this year.</p><p>We'll see what that entails but it might take the form of having more discipline around sending out some thoughts in the <a href='{{' title=site.subscribe_email }}>newsletter</a>.</p><p>Have any book recommendations? Please shoot me an email or leave a comment.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2021/01/24/reading-in-2020/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2020]]></title>
    <updated>2021-01-24T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year I reflect on my reading from the previous year. I take a look at my records, fix errors, and think about reading goals for the upcoming year.</p><p>Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>, and <a href='/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/'>2019</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?shelf=read_2020'>Here</a> is my 2020.</p><h2>2020 Goals</h2><p>Last year I wrote:</p><blockquote><p> I was encouraged by how many non-fiction books I read this year and how many of them ended up earning a five star rating. I'd like to continue that trend of reading high-quality non-fiction books. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> I've also been reading a lot of books but I haven't always been the best at trying to consciously apply the lessons from those books. I'm going to try to improve that this year. </p></blockquote><blockquote><p> Those are pretty fuzzy goals but I'm alright with that. </p></blockquote><p>I'll come back at the end of this article and reflect on if I hit it or not.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Here are my five star books from 2020. The titles are Amazon.</p><p>If I wrote a review on Goodreads then the <code>my review</code> link will take you there. In the last couple of years, I've been writing fewer reviews on Goodreads than in the past so many books do not have a review there.</p><p>If you're missing these reviews, I have started sending out an email every month or two and it frequently includes small reviews of what I've read since the previous email. You can subscribe to that <a href='{{' title=site.subscribe_email }}>here</a>.</p><p>Here are the 2020 five star books:</p><ul><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Hard-Truth-Simple-Become-Climber/dp/1734103604'>The Hard Truth: Simple Ways to Become a Better Climber</a> by Kris Hampton (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3315020265'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Body-Keeps-Score-Healing-Trauma/dp/0143127748'>The Body Keeps the Score: Brain, Mind, and Body in the Healing of Trauma</a> by Bessel A. van der Kolk</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Come-You-Are-Surprising-Transform/dp/1476762090'>Come as You Are: The Surprising New Science that Will Transform Your Sex Life</a> by Emily Nagoski</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Change-Your-Mind-Consciousness-Transcendence/dp/0735224153'>How to Change Your Mind: What the New Science of Psychedelics Teaches Us About Consciousness, Dying, Addiction, Depression, and Transcendence</a> by Michael Pollan</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Longer-Talking-White-People-About-ebook/dp/B06WWPX2YF'>Why I’m No Longer Talking to White People About Race</a> by Reni Eddo-Lodge</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Ijeawele-Feminist-Manifesto-Fifteen-Suggestions/dp/0525434801'>Dear Ijeawele; or, A Feminist Manifesto in Fifteen Suggestions</a> by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Americanah-Ala-Notable-Books-Adults-ebook/dp/B00A9ET4MC'>Americanah</a> by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Half-Yellow-Chimamanda-Ngozi-Adichie/dp/1400095204'>Half of a Yellow Sun</a> by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Diamond-Age-Illustrated-Primer-Spectra-ebook/dp/B000FBJCKI'>The Diamond Age</a> by Neal Stephenson (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/94072683'>my review</a>)</li><li>Parable of the Sower (Earthseed, #1) by Octavia E. Butler</li><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Parable-Sower-Octavia-Butler/dp/1538732181'>Parable of the Talents (Earthseed, #2)</a> by Octavia E. Butler</li></ul><h4>The Hard Truth: Simple Ways to Become a Better Climber by Kris Hampton</h4><p>This is an excellent dose of wisdom about climbing and improving your performance. It does this through suggestions of how to change your mental relationship with climbing. Improving is about putting in the work, reflecting, and trying hard.</p><h4>The Body Keeps the Score: Brain, Mind, and Body in the Healing of Trauma by Bessel A. van der Kolk</h4><p>I really enjoyed this book and made hundreds of highlights while reading it on my Kindle. I'd suggest reading reviews on <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22268254-the-body-keeps-the-score'>Goodreads</a> and seeing if it is something that would be interesting for you.</p><h4>Come as You Are: The Surprising New Science that Will Transform Your Sex Life by Emily Nagoski</h4><p>This was a good book that, unlike what the subtitle claims, did not transform my sex life. But I didn't go into it expecting that. I'm not the main audience for this book but still got some value from it. I particularly enjoyed the parts that talked about stress, responses to stress, and emotional systems.</p><h4>How to Change Your Mind by Michael Pollan</h4><p>This book is about psychedelics, such as LSD and psilocybin. It combines the history of these substances, old and new research being done with them, and sort of a travelogue of Michael Pollan's growing experience with these substances.</p><h4>Why I’m No Longer Talking to White People About Race by Reni Eddo-Lodge</h4><p>I'll just link to a <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2697985490?book_show_action=false'>friend's review</a> of this book.</p><h4>The author Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie</h4><p>I devoured all of her writing this year, both fiction and non-fiction, and the highlights are above. None of her writing earned less than four stars.</p><p>Between starting and finishing writing this article, I learned she published a new short story, <i>Zikora</i>, and immediately read it. It was pretty great.</p><p>One of the reasons I enjoy reading fiction is that it provides a window into the experiences of others. Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie's writing does exactly this and does it with beautiful prose and compelling stories.</p><h4>The Diamond Age by Neal Stephenson</h4><p>This was a reread of the first Neal Stephenson book I read. I wanted to reread this book as I had been recommending it as a relatively short introduction to Neal Stephenson's writing but I was second guessing how much I enjoyed it.</p><p>I was wrong to second guess that. This story was still great the second time through. This book covers so much and feels prescient despite being read 25 years after it was originally published (February 1995).</p><h4>Parable of the Sower and Parable of the Talents by Octavia E. Butler</h4><p>Octavia Butler builds a new religion in this series and, honestly, that religion is tempting. These are fantastic science fiction reads that explore human connections and what we could be as a species.</p><h3>Other notable reads</h3><p>These are books that for some reason I didn't give five stars but I still think they are worth recommending. All links below are to Goodreads.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52702097-piranesi'>Piranesi</a> by Susanna Clark</h4><p>This book was weird and I enjoyed it. You follow a character that lives in a weird, infinite building made of corridors lined with statues.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52655150-why-we-re-polarized'>Why We're Polarized</a> by Ezra Klein</h4><p>This covers the American political system and how we got to our modern form with deeply polarized parties. I thought it was a pretty interesting read.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6656720-the-will-to-change'>The Will to Change: Men, Masculinity, and Love</a> by bell hooks</h4><p>I read this at the very beginning of 2020 and think that everyone should read it. I highlighted a ton of passages and plan on going back and reviewing those passages.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52355815-you-re-not-listening'>You're Not Listening: What You're Missing and Why It Matters</a> by Kate Murphy</h4><p>I read this at the very beginning of 2020 and highlighted a ton of passages. The book is about listening and how we do a bad job at it. It includes suggestions about how to get better.</p><p>Pair this book with <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35522033-i-hear-you'>I hear you</a>, a book I read last year, and you'll have the tools to become a better listener.</p><h4><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18886790-diaspora'>Diaspora</a> by Greg Egan</h4><p>This was a stupendous science fiction read. It takes you on a wild journey into a far future where sentient beings can exist in software.</p><p>This was very close to receiving five stars but I kept getting bogged down in some of the explanations. I know this is why some folks enjoy hard science fiction but that isn't why I'm reading these stories. This book delivers an interesting, complex, and very speculative far future. If the blurb sounds interesting to you and you're willing to put up some with advanced theoretical (real? fake? I don't know) physics then pick this book up.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>I read 43 books and 12,093 pages in 2020. The data also doesn't capture three books that I've started but have yet to finish.</p><pre><code class="language-org">| Year | # of Pages | # of Books |
|------+------------+------------|
| 2020 |      12093 |         43 |
| 2019 |      15994 |         42 |
| 2018 |      13538 |         36 |
| 2017 |      18317 |         48 |
| 2016 |      22790 |         59 |
| 2015 |      21689 |         51 |
| 2014 |      24340 |         71 |
| 2013 |      19815 |         60 |
| 2012 |      14208 |         44 |
| 2011 |       9179 |         19 |
| 2010 |      14667 |         46 |
</code></pre><p>Last year marks a decade of me tracking my reading and it was the second lowest page count in that decade. For many reasons 2020 was an unforgettable year and one where I spent a lot of time at home.</p><p>I would have thought that would have lead to a large number of pages read but I think much of my time ended up being taken up by non-book reading activities. For better or worse (probably worse), a lot of my time was spent reading articles about the on-going global pandemic, the USA election, and the other non-stop news cycle of 2020. Between that and the increase in newsletters and podcasts I'm consuming, I'm not that surprised my book reading has taken a hit.</p><p>Here is a breakdown of books finished by month.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-2020/books-by-month-2020.png" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books and pages for each month" /></p><p>This graph tells a slightly different story than the one I presented above. I did not finish many pages in January through March, the pre-pandemic time period in the United States.</p><p>Those months I was extremely dedicated to training for climbing and was starting a new relationship. I'm very happy both of those took up my non-working hours during those months.</p><p>I was still commuting to an office from January till mid-March and would have expected more pages finished on the train. I'll blame podcasts for that as this year I did start listening to those while commuting, since I can enjoy those while walking to and from the train as well.</p><p>The number of books read in February is high because I read a short story collection where each story was published individually on Amazon.</p><p>Unsurprisingly, electronic books continue to be the dominant format.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|           | 2020 | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------+------|
| audiobook |    1 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |    0 |
| ebook     |   41 |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    0 |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    1 |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>Below is the breakdown of fiction vs non-fiction books. Fiction started to regain its dominance after having non-fiction catch up in 2019.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|                           |   2020 |   2019 |   2018 |
|---------------------------+--------+--------+--------|
| fiction                   |     26 |     28 |     29 |
| non-fiction               |     17 |     23 |     14 |
| fiction:non-fiction ratio | 1.53:1 | 1.22:1 | 2.07:1 |

</code></pre><p>Here is the star rating distribution.</p><pre><code class="language-org">|             | 2 stars | 3 stars | 4 stars | 5 stars |
|-------------+---------+---------+---------+---------|
| fiction     |       1 |       8 |      12 |       5 |
| non-fiction |       0 |       4 |       7 |       6 |
</code></pre><h2>Did I hit my 2020 goals?</h2><p>I succeeded in reading a solid number of non-fiction books that earned a high rating. I read fewer non-fiction books than fiction but managed to have more 5 star ratings. I'm going to count this as successfully hitting the non-fiction part of my 2020 goal.</p><p>Did I get better at applying the lessons from books? Not at all and I barely even tried to do so. Definite failure here.</p><h2>2021 goals</h2><p>I have quite a few unread books sitting on my virtual and physical bookshelf. This feels like setting a really low-bar but this year I'd like to read some of these unread-but-owned books.</p><p>I'm also planning on reading at least one book on writing and one book on climbing. This goal is almost a subset of the above goal as I have books on both these topics sitting on my shelf.</p><p>It is interesting to have been collecting this data for a decade now. I haven't done much in the way around looking at multi-year trends but I think it might be interesting to do so.</p><p>If you have a book recommendation, feel free to reach out and contact me.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/01/11/reading-in-2019/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2019]]></title>
    <updated>2020-01-11T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year I reflect on the previous year of reading. I take a look at my records, fix errors, and think about reading goals for the upcoming year.</p><p>Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>, and <a href='/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/'>2018</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> has nearly the full list of the books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?shelf=read_2019'>This</a> is my 2019.</p><h2>2019 Goal</h2><blockquote><p> I have a stack of software and process books and I'd like to read through at least some of them (others are more reference books). I'm also going to bring over the 2018 goal of reading at least one book on writing. In a more general sense, I'm hoping to put some practices together that help me gain more from the books I'm reading. I'm still thinking through what that means. - Me last year </p></blockquote><p>That was my goal for 2019. In list form it looks like this:</p><ol><li>Read some software or process books</li><li>Read at least one book on writing</li><li>Try to develop practices for getting more from books I've read</li></ol><p>I read eight books related to the first goal and two (or three if I count an iffy one) related to the second. That is enough where I feel pretty good about claiming I accomplished the first two goals.</p><p>I mostly failed on the third goal. I was more aggressive about highlighting notes in my Kindle and I did occasionally look back at them. Beyond that I didn't do anything.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Here are my five star books from 2019.</p><ul><li>Accelerate: Building and Scaling High-Performing Technology Organizations by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble, and Gene Kim (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2411886698'>my review</a>)</li><li>Elements of Clojure by Zachary Tellman (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2684688658'>my review</a>)</li><li>A Tour of C++ by Bjarne Stroustrup (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2822201641'>my review</a>)</li><li>Developer Hegemony: The Future of Labor (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2795008954'>my review</a>)</li><li>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World by Cal Newport</li><li>Effective Java by Joshua Bloch (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2701581699'>my review</a>)</li><li>21 Lessons for the 21st Century by Yuval Noah Harari (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2562286276'>my review</a>)</li><li>Draft No. 4: On the Writing Process by John McPhee (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2300752363'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Push: A Climber's Journey of Endurance, Risk and Going Beyond Limits by Tommy Caldwell (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2200390288'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Nickel Boys by Colson Whitehead</li><li>The Great Believers by Rebecca Makkai (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/3020415147'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Bonfire of the Vanities by Tom Wolfe (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2847590304'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Paper Menagerie and Other Stories by Ken Liu (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1827462108'>my review</a>)</li><li>Exhalation: Stories by Ted Chiang (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2804306157'>my review</a>)</li><li>Golden Son (Red Rising, #2) by Pierce Brown</li><li>Morning Star (Red Rising Saga, #3) by Pierce Brown</li><li>Iron Gold (Red Rising Saga, #4) by Pierce Brown (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2760320870'>my review</a>)</li><li>Dark Age (Red Rising Saga #5) by Pierce Brown</li><li>Animal Farm by George Orwell (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2811868686'>my review</a>)</li></ul><h4>Accelerate: Building and Scaling High-Performing Technology Organizations by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble, and Gene Kim</h4><p>This is a stellar book on practices of technology organizations that help build high performing companies. If you work at a company that produces software in any capacity, I'd highly recommend this book. This is a book that I've recommended to any coworker looking, and some not looking, for book recommendations.</p><h4>Elements of Clojure by Zachary Tellman</h4><p>This book has Clojure in the title but it is applicable to more than that language. The book was published a section at a time and as a result I've read parts of it many times. The content clearly shows that Zach has put a lot of thought into the topic.</p><h4>A Tour of C++ by Bjarne Stroustrup</h4><p>I've written C++ off and on since I started programming nearly 20 years ago. Over those years, I've seen C++ transform as new versions were released. Earlier in 2019, I was starting to write C++ again and this book was recommended by a coworker. I had last written C++ back in 2013 and this book was a perfect way to refresh my stuck in early 2013 knowledge. There is no fluff in this book and it is full of useful information.</p><h4>Developer Hegemony: The Future of Labor</h4><p>This is a tough read. It isn't tough because of difficult writing. It is tough because it makes you depressed until you power through and reach the end.</p><p>This book delivers a very cynical look at corporations. It provides guidelines for getting ahead and climbing the corporate ladder.</p><p>Then the book promotes an alternative approach, that of doing your own thing and going independent. It makes a good case of it.</p><p>Beware of this one, it might make you question what you are doing with your career and life.</p><h4>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World by Cal Newport</h4><p>There is a common theme of awareness throughout many of the books I read and this book hits that theme. This book can help you become a more thoughtful user of technology. There are many useful recommendations in this book. One of them is the suggestion that you can use social media and other technology differently than how the creators want you to use it. In 2019 I wrote about how I use <a href='/blog/2019/04/30/how-i-use-social-media/'>social media</a> which shows how I apply this idea.</p><h4>Effective Java by Joshua Bloch</h4><p>I've read earlier editions in the past and decided to read the latest edition when it seemed like I'd be writing Java again. This book is still good and a must read if you work with Java.</p><h4>21 Lessons for the 21st Century by Yuval Noah Harari</h4><p>This book covers a lot of ground.</p><p>Here is a quote from my friend <a href='https://twitter.com/deobald'>Steven Deobald</a> about this book.</p><blockquote><p> Through stories and anecdotes woven into his almost unbelievably extensive research as a historian, "21 Lessons" is perhaps as entertaining and insightful as any other book I've read. It is accessible to anyone and the ideas presented regarding the fate of our species are stitched together beautifully. The arc of the 21 chapters has a progressive, almost orchestral, quality to it. Each chapter builds on all those which precede it and although some chapters have surprisingly variable writing styles, none feels like Harari is attempting to showboat or to force his medium into the overly artistic. </p></blockquote><h4>Draft No. 4: On the Writing Process by John McPhee</h4><p>This was a pleasure to read. I like reading books about writing and this is a good one that talks about McPhee's approach towards creative non-fiction.</p><h4>The Push: A Climber's Journey of Endurance, Risk and Going Beyond Limits by Tommy Caldwell</h4><p>What can I say? I'm a sucker for books on climbing and learning more about the icons of the sport I love. If you've watched the movie <a href='https://www.imdb.com/title/tt7286916/'>The Dawn Wall</a> then some of this will be familiar to you.</p><h4>The Nickel Boys by Colson Whitehead</h4><p>This is a great book. Go read the <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42270835-the-nickel-boys'>Goodreads</a> page and pick it up.</p><h4>The Great Believers by Rebecca Makkai</h4><p>A friend of mine gave me a copy of this book and I'm glad she did. It tells the story of the AIDs epidemic in Chicago. This is a great piece of writing. I'm not surprised at all that it has won many awards.</p><h4>The Bonfire of the Vanities by Tom Wolfe</h4><p>This book is great. The satire just drips off the pages. There are passages in this book where you can just <i>feel</i> the anxiety of the characters.</p><p>Every character is despicable and it is wonderful.</p><h4>The Paper Menagerie and Other Stories by Ken Liu</h4><p>This was my second time reading this book. It is an excellent collection of short stories.</p><p>The first time I read this book, in <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, I read the stories in order. This time I took advantage of the Kindle's estimate of how long a chapter would take and I jumped around, picking out stories that fit how long I wanted to read. Both ways of reading this collection were excellent.</p><h4>Exhalation: Stories by Ted Chiang</h4><p>I absolutely loved Ted Chiang's <i>Stories of Your Life and Others</i> and was excited when this collection of stories was published. I had high hopes for this collection and I was not disappointed.</p><p>Some of the stories I had read prior to them being included in this collection but that didn't matter. I enjoyed reading the new stories and revisiting the previously published ones.</p><blockquote><p> We don’t normally think of it as such, but writing is a technology, which means that a literate person is someone whose thought processes are technologically mediated. We became cognitive cyborgs as soon as we became fluent readers, and the consequences of that were profound. </p></blockquote><p>That is a quote from a story in this collection. It felt right to include it in an article about reading.</p><h4>Golden Son, Morning Star, Iron Gold, and Dark Age by Pierce Brown</h4><p>The four titles above are books two through five in Pierce Brown's <i>Red Rising</i> saga. I also read the first book in the series, Red Rising, in 2019 but it only earned a four star rating from me. I obviously enjoyed this series and devoured it.</p><p>The books tell the story of a world full of inequality. The world created is full of interesting characters and dilemmas.</p><h4>Animal Farm by George Orwell</h4><p>This was either my second or third time reading Animal Farm. It is still good. Reading it in 2019 and mapping in book behavior to the modern political climate was interesting.</p><h3>Non-Five Star highlights</h3><ul><li>Irresistible: The Rise of Addictive Technology and the Business of Keeping Us Hooked by Adam Alter (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1966643946'>my review</a>)</li><li>Permanent Record by Edward Snowden (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2983575511'>my review</a>)</li><li>Atonement by Ian McEwan (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1697924044'>my review</a>)</li><li>I Hear You by Michael S. Sorensen (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2923747300'>my review</a>)</li><li>Recursion by Blake Crouch (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2923743967'>my review</a>)</li><li>Version Control by Dexter Palmer (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1827462266'>my review</a>)</li></ul><h4>Irresistible: The Rise of Addictive Technology and the Business of Keeping Us Hooked by Adam Alter</h4><p>Yet another book that is at least somewhat about awareness. This book talks about behavioral addiction but not just addictive technology.</p><p>Is it the single book out of the handful of books I've read in this space that I'd recommend? No, but it is a good addition to my collection on the topic.</p><h4>Permanent Record by Edward Snowden</h4><p>I consider myself fairly knowledgeable about Snowden and what he did but I still learned more through this book. One part I particularly enjoyed was Snowden reflecting on what has changed since his actions.</p><p>Another part I particularly enjoyed was Snowden's telling of the early Internet. This was an Internet where identities online weren't necessarily tied to a real one. I'm approximately the same age as Snowden and had similar experiences with being a young person during the early Internet days. It was interesting to be reminded of that time while reading this book.</p><p>I <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/49833241-permanent-record/3431614-jake-mccrary?ref=bsop'>highlighted</a> a lot of passages and there are probably more I should have highlighted.</p><h4>Atonement by Ian McEwan</h4><p>This book was so close to being five stars. I started reading this book because I mistook the title for that of a science fiction book I've been intending to read. I'm glad I did.</p><p>It took me a little while to get into the book but once I did I was hooked.</p><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1697596771?book_show_action=false'>Here</a> is a review from one of my friends that captures some of what I felt about this book.</p><h4>I Hear You by Michael S. Sorensen</h4><p>It provides some guidance towards being a more validating person. The book is short and to the point. I've managed to take some of its advice and I think it has been useful.</p><h4>Recursion by Blake Crouch</h4><p>This was really good. It is action packed and an interesting concept.</p><h4>Version Control by Dexter Palmer</h4><p>I really enjoy this book. It tells the story of a relationship with bits of science fiction. I really enjoyed my friend <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2240581079?book_show_action=false'>Dan's</a> review.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>The page count numbers for 2019 books are a bit screwed up so I'm only doing a books per month graph this year.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2019.svg" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Number of books in each month" /></p><p>Unsurprisingly, electronic books continue to be the dominate format.</p><pre><code>|           | 2019 | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------+------|
| ebook     |   43 |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    1 |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    7 |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>This year I read a noticeably higher amount of non-fiction books than in 2018.</p><pre><code>|             | 2019 | 2018 |
|-------------+------+------|
| fiction     |   28 |   29 |
| non-fiction |   23 |   14 |
</code></pre><h2>2020 Goals</h2><p>I was encouraged by how many non-fiction books I read this year and how many of them ended up earning a five star rating. I'd like to continue that trend of reading high-quality non-fiction books.</p><p>I've also been reading a lot of books but I haven't always been the best at trying to consciously apply the lessons from those books. I'm going to try to improve that this year.</p><p>Those are pretty fuzzy goals but I'm alright with that.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2019/01/21/reading-in-2018/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2018]]></title>
    <updated>2019-01-21T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of every year I like to take the time to reflect on my previous year's reading. It gives me a time to correct my data and think about where I want my reading to go in the upcoming year.</p><p>Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>, and <a href='/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/'>2017</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> continues to have the full list of the books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?read_at=2018'>Here</a> is my entire 2018 record.</p><p>I slacked off a bit when writing reviews for all of my read books in Goodreads. I often didn't write a review until some time had passed after completing the book and, as a result, I think I did a worse job reviewing books. Some books don't even have a written review. I'm not a fan of this and will push myself some in 2019 to do a better job.</p><h2>2018 Goal</h2><blockquote><p> There are a few more books on writing that I've wanted to read for a while. I'm planning on reading at least one of them this year. I'm also want to read more Octavia Butler. - Me (in the previous reading post) </p></blockquote><p>That was my goal for 2018. It breaks down into two goals:</p><ol><li>Read at least one book on writing.</li><li>Read more Octavia Butler.</li></ol><p>I succeeded on the Octavia Butler goal and completely failed with the other.</p><h2>2018 Numbers</h2><p>I read 43 books for a total of 16,213 pages. This is a bit less than last year but still a fair amount.</p><h2>Highlights</h2><p>Below is a list of my five star books from 2018. I've linked to my Goodreads reviews when I've written one.  Unfortunately, this year I didn't do a great job of always writing a review so some of them are missing or very short.</p><p>I generally highlight a lot of passages while reading and then rarely go back to look at them. I've included links to my highlights. Are they worthwhile without the context of the book? I have no idea. I've reread them and got something out of them but many are also so far removed from my memory that they are almost useless.</p><ul><li>Being Mortal: Medicine and What Matters in the End by Atul Gawande (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1380346555'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/23290548-being-mortal/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a>)</li><li>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind by Yuval Noah Harari (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1679140092'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/20873740-sapiens/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a>)</li><li>Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less by Greg McKeown (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1178908716'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/19776547-essentialism/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a>)</li><li>Crucial Conversations Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High by Kerry Patterson,  Joseph Grenny, Ron McMillan, Al Switzler (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/13041257-crucial-conversations-tools-for-talking-when-stakes-are-high/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a>)</li><li>Rediscovering JavaScript: Master ES6, ES7, and ES8 by Venkat Subramaniam (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2450809712'>my review</a>)</li><li>CivilWarLand in Bad Decline by George Saunders (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/104227855'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Obelisk Gate (The Broken Earth #2) by N.K. Jemisin</li><li>The Stone Sky (The Broken Earth, #3) by N.K. Jemisin (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2467372092'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Hate U Give by Angie Thomas (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2221117127'>my review</a>)</li><li>Six of Crows (Six of Crows, #1) by Leigh Bardugo (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2309941150'>my review</a>)</li><li>Crooked Kingdom (Six of Crows #2) by Leigh Bardugo</li></ul><h4>Being Mortal: Medicine and What Matters in the End by Atul Gawande</h4><p>This book deals with the end of our lives. It was great. There is a lot of good insight here. Like a lot of the non-fiction books I read, I really should go back and take notes on what I highlighted.</p><p>We're all going to deal with death and sickness. This book can help.</p><h4>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind by Yuval Noah Harari</h4><p>My entire Goodreads review is two sentences.</p><blockquote><p> This is an incredible book. You should read this. - Me </p></blockquote><p>I still agree with this. My friend, Steve Deobald, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2347504001?book_show_action=false'>described</a> this book as "the most lucid book he's ever read." There is a reason this book has a 4.45 rating on Goodreads. Go read the blurb about it there and then buy and read this book<a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>.</p><h4>Essentialism: The Disciplined Pursuit of Less by Greg McKeown</h4><blockquote><p> If you don’t prioritize your life, someone else will. - Greg McKeown </p></blockquote><p>A really great book encouraging you to focus on what matters and, as a result, make a bigger impact and be happier. It is better to make a mile of progress on one thing instead of making inches of progress in a bunch. </p><p>Tim Ferris recently <a href='https://tim.blog/2019/01/09/greg-mckeown-essentialism/'>published a podcast</a> with Greg McKeown which I'd also recommend. I've enjoyed listening to the podcast after a bit of time away from the book. This has helped reinforce ideas from the book. If you're hesitant to read the book, take the time to listen and pay attention to this long podcast.</p><p>I highlighted over 100 sections of this book. I plan on revisiting these notes and this book periodically.</p><h4>Crucial Conversations Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High by Kerry Patterson, Joseph Grenny, Ron McMillan, Al Switzler</h4><p>A crucial conversation is one where the stakes are high, opinions vary, and emotions run strong. This book provides guidance for handling those conversations better.</p><p>I enjoyed this book and thought I picked up some useful tips from it. I think this is another where doing follow up work would help solidify some of the concepts.</p><h4>Rediscovering JavaScript: Master ES6, ES7, and ES8 by Venkat Subramaniam</h4><p>Do you write JavaScript?</p><p>Did you write JavaScript in the past but then move on to languages like ClojureScript and miss all the changes that happened to JavaScript?</p><p>Both of those sentences apply to me. This book has been great at catching up on modern JavaScript. I find myself referencing it while writing JavaScript and it has been very helpful. It is to the point and I find myself referencing it periodically.</p><h4>CivilWarLand in Bad Decline by George Saunders</h4><p>I really like this book. It is a wonderful collection of short stories. This was my second time reading it and I still enjoyed it.</p><h4>The Obelisk Gate (The Broken Earth #2) and The Stone Sky (The Broken Earth, #3) by N.K. Jemisin</h4><p>N.K. Jemisin has won a Hugo three years in a row. Those three years line up with each release of a book in The Broken Earth series. They are really good.</p><p>This series is great. The world is interesting and the story compelling. I highly recommend it.</p><h4>The Hate U Give by Angie Thomas</h4><p>Reading lets you experience life from a different perspective. This book is good. It was quickly made into a movie which is also pretty good.</p><p>I read this as part of my book club and it was universally enjoyed.</p><h4>Six of Crows (Six of Crows, #1) and Crooked Kingdom (Six of Crows #2) by Leigh Bardugo</h4><p>I just really enjoyed this series. I enjoyed the fantasy world it was set in and have read most of Leigh Bardugo's other books that are set in this same world.</p><p>The series is a young adult series. It isn't complex. The reading isn't difficult. It isn't going to change your life and you're not going to be blown away by the writing. It almost feels weird to include this series in the same list as CivilWarLand and The Broken Earth series. Even still, I found myself sucked into the story and didn't mind spending the short amount of time it took to read the books.</p><h3>Non-Five Star highlights</h3><h4>Life 3.0: Being Human in the Age of Artificial Intelligence by Max Tegmark</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/35881748-life-3-0/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a></p><p>I thought this was a really interesting book.</p><h4>When: The Scientific Secrets of Perfect Timing by Daniel H. Pink</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2278408888'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/35786699-when/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a></p><p>I really enjoyed this. Pink references other works to build a narrative about how timing matters. When should you take a nap? Is it better to go do the doctors in the morning or afternoon? How do are cognitive abilities generally change throughout the day? How should you try to end your vacations?</p><p>I did take some notes on the book while reading it and I have referenced them. It was a good book. I should have taken more notes.</p><h4>Bloodchild and Other Stories by Octavia E. Butler</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2293497979'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/40274755-bloodchild-and-other-stories/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a></p><p>This is a great collection of short stories and non-fiction articles written by Octavia Butler. I really love her writing. I've read a few of her works and still enjoy <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/60926.Lilith_s_Brood'>Lilith's Brood</a> the most.</p><p>Below is a quote from her about science fiction that really resonated with me. It really hits home on one of the reasons I love reading science fiction.</p><blockquote><p> But still I’m asked, what good is science fiction to Black people? What good is any form of literature to Black people? What good is science fiction’s thinking about the present, the future, and the past? What good is its tendency to warn or to consider alternative ways of thinking and doing? What good is its examination of the possible effects of science and technology, or social organization and political direction? At its best, science fiction stimulates imagination and creativity. It gets reader and writer off the beaten track, off the narrow, narrow footpath of what “everyone” is saying, doing, thinking—whoever “everyone” happens to be this year. And what good is all this to Black people? - Octavia Butler </p></blockquote><h4>Eeeee Eee Eeee by Tao Lin</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1788752328'>my review</a></p><p>This book is real bizarre. For some reason I liked it.</p><h4>Factfulness: Ten Reasons We're Wrong About the World&ndash;and Why Things Are Better Than You Think by Hans Rosling</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2402596250'>my review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/notes/36185940-factfulness/3431614-jake-mccrary'>my highlights</a></p><p>This book is great. It is very approachable and dispels some wrong common knowledge.</p><h2>Stats</h2><p>I struggled generating stats this year. I kept having data issues with Goodreads. There is data that is in Goodreads that is failing to export both through their export feature and API. I'm somewhat wondering what I would need to do to track reading in a different way.</p><p>Below is the reading stats per month. The numbers are based on when the book is completed. December is partially so low because the other books all carried over to January.</p><p><img src="/images/2018-books-and-pages.svg" alt="Book and pages count by month" title="Book and pages count by month" /></p><p>Electronic books continue to make up the majority of the books I'm reading.</p><pre><code>|           | 2018 | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------+------|
| ebook     |   37 |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    1 |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    5 |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>There are two physical books not included in my read books that I started and still need to finish. They are a both books focused on fitness (climbing injuries and proper movement) and aren't books I'm actively reading.</p><p>Nearly a third of my reading was non-fiction. For the second year in a row, only two of those were software related.</p><pre><code>|             | Number of books |
|-------------+-----------------|
| fiction     |              29 |
| non-fiction |              14 |
</code></pre><h2>2019 Goals</h2><p>I have a stack of software and process books and I'd like to read through at least some of them (others are more reference books). I'm also going to bring over the 2018 goal of reading at least one book on writing.</p><p>In a more general sense, I'm hoping to put some practices together that help me gain more from the books I'm reading. I'm still thinking through what that means. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>In the beginning of 2019 I also read Harari's "21 lessons for the 21st Century." Spoiler alert: this book will end up in my 2019 reading summary post.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2018/03/03/reading-in-2017/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2017]]></title>
    <updated>2018-03-03T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I typically like to reflect on my previous years reading closer to the beginning of the next year. We are just entering March, so I've missed doing that.</p><p>Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>, <a href='/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/'>2016</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> continues to have the full list of the books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?read_at=2017'>Here</a> is my entire 2017 record.</p><h2>2017 Goal</h2><p>My goal entering 2017 was to revisit some past favorites. I started this goal without setting a number, so I'll just have to trust how I feel about it.</p><p>In 2017, I reread Frank Herbert's Dune and John William's Stoner. I also read new-to-me books by the authors David Foster Wallace, Haruki Murakami, George Saunders, and Neal Stephenson. I've also reread a George Saunders book in the first part of 2018.</p><p>I mostly achieved 2017's goal. If I had reread another book, I'd consider it 100% completed, but I'm going to count reading some favorite authors towards the goal.</p><h2>2017 Numbers</h2><p>I read a total of 49 books for a total of 17,853 pages. I also read every issue of Amazon's <em>Day One</em> weekly periodical<a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>.</p><p>The number of five-star books I read this last year was low compared to previous years.</p><h2>Recommendations</h2><p>I only gave out seven five-star ratings. Two of the seven were books I reread.The review links are to my review on Goodreads.</p><ul><li>Stories of Your Life and Others - Ted Chiang (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1868465450'>my review</a>)</li><li>A Supposedly Fun Thing I'll Never Do Again: Essays and Arguments - David Foster Wallace (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1071157288'>my review</a>)</li><li>Dune - Frank Herbert (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2200354838'>my review</a>)</li><li>Lilith's Brood - Octavia Butler (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2136588256'>my review</a>)</li><li>Stoner - John Williams (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1896951901'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Sense of Style: The Thinking Person's Guide to Writing in the 21st Century - Steven Pinker (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1216210735'>my review</a>)</li><li>Shoe Dog - Phil Knight (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1866261263'>my review</a>)</li></ul><p>Below are more details on some of the above five-star books and some shoutouts for some non-five star books. Looking back over my books, I'd recommend any four-star or higher book without hesitation but am not going to put them all here.</p><h4><em>Lilith's Brood</em> by Octavia Butler</h4><p><em>Lilith's Brood</em> was one of the last books I read in 2017. It is a three book series published as a single book. It is amazing. This series achieves precisely what I want in a great science fiction book. I highly recommend this book. Reading this book reminded me why I love reading.</p><p>A quote from a non-fiction essay by Octavia Butler describes why good science fiction is fantastic.</p><blockquote><p> But still I’m asked, what good is science fiction to Black people? What good is any form of literature to Black people? What good is science fiction’s thinking about the present, the future, and the past? What good is its tendency to warn or to consider alternative ways of thinking and doing? What good is its examination of the possible effects of science and technology, or social organization and political direction? At its best, science fiction stimulates imagination and creativity. It gets reader and writer off the beaten track, off the narrow, narrow footpath of what “everyone” is saying, doing, thinking—whoever “everyone” happens to be this year. And what good is all this to Black people? - <strong>Octavia Butler</strong> </p></blockquote><h4><em>The Sense of Style</em> by Steven Pinker</h4><p>Yes, I read a book on writing and think this is one of the top books I read last year. I initially read a Kindle edition from my local library and then immediately bought the hardcover so I can reference it while writing.</p><p>The writing is great. The book is humorous. I'd highly recommend to anyone that writes. I should reread this.</p><h4><em>Dune</em> by Frank Herbert</h4><p><em>Dune</em> is a classic for a reason. It was still great my second time through it. If you haven't read Dune, you are missing out.</p><p>If you read it on a Kindle, I have a <a href='http://gum.co/dune-dictionary'>custom Kindle dictionary</a> that makes reading it more pleasurable.</p><h4><em>Stoner</em> by John Williams</h4><p>It is still unclear to me why I like this book so much, but I do. The writing is crisp. The story is depressing.</p><h4><em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em> by Ted Chiang</h4><p>Over the years I've started to enjoy reading short story collections. Every story in this collection was great. I devoured this book and then everything else I could find by Ted Chiang.</p><h4><em>Capital in the Twenty-First Century</em> by Thomas Piketty</h4><p>This is a massive book. It probably deserved five-stars. It presents a ton of information to the reader. It is boring. It also made me think about the role of taxes in society and changed my thoughts about them.</p><p>If you've been putting this off, you can probably skip to the last section and still get a lot from this book.</p><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/926621222?book_show_action=true'>Here</a> is a review that does a spot on job of describing the book and <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/2041297829'>my own review</a>.</p><h4>Bobiverse Series by Dennis Taylor</h4><p><a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/192752-bobiverse'>This</a> is a fun light-hearted science fiction series. It still manages to explore some deep topics. Read the description and if it sounds interesting to you, pick it up. </p><h2>Stats</h2> <p>Similar to last year, April and September were times when I wasn't reading a ton.</p><p><img src="/images/reading-by-month-2017.jpg" alt="Chart of reading per month" title="Chart of reading per month" /></p><p>This year physical books made a comeback. I checked out more physical books from the library this year than in the past.</p><pre><code>|           | 2017 | 2016 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------+------|
| ebook     |   37 |   56 |   47 |
| hardcover |    7 |    0 |    1 |
| paperback |    5 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>My average rating went down a bit.</p><pre><code>| Year | Avg Rating |
|------+------------|
| 2011 |       3.84 |
| 2012 |       3.66 |
| 2013 |       3.55 |
| 2014 |       3.49 |
| 2015 |       3.86 |
| 2016 |       3.85 |
| 2017 |       3.77 |
</code></pre><p>I read a lot of non-fiction books this year. Only two of them were directly related to software.</p><pre><code>|             | Number of books |
|-------------+-----------------|
| fiction     |              30 |
| non-fiction |              19 |

</code></pre><h2>2018 Goals</h2><p>There are a few more books on writing that I've wanted to read for a while. I'm planning on reading at least one of them this year. I'm also want to read more Octavia Butler. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>Unfortunately, this periodical has ended after years of publishing once a week. I'm bummed. I really enjoyed receiving a short story and poem once a week.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/01/04/reading-in-2016/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2016]]></title>
    <updated>2017-01-04T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The time has come for another end-of-year summary of my reading from the previous year. Here are links to my previous end-of-year reflections: <a href='//jakemccrary.com/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a>, <a href='//jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a>, <a href='//jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/'>2015</a>.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> contains the full list and reviews of books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?read_at=2016'>Here</a> is my full 2016 list.</p><h2>2016 Goal</h2><p>My 2016 goal was to read one or two biographies. It is a genre that I typically don't read and I felt like branching out. I'm going to consider this goal achieved. I read <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Open-Autobiography-Andre-Agassi/dp/0307388409'>Open</a> (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1679109928'>my review</a>) by Andre Agassi (well, ghostwritten for him) and <a href='http://amzn.to/2iQrZkG'>Medium Raw</a> by Anthony Bourdain. Both have been tagged as memoirs so in the strictest sense maybe I shouldn't count them towards my goal but I'm counting them. <em>Open</em> tells Andre Agassi's life story and claims to have been fact checked so it is pretty close to a biography.</p><p>Of the two, I drastically preferred <em>Open</em>. I would not recommend <em>Medium Raw</em> unless you know you like Bourdain's writing and the book description sounds interesting to you. <em>Open</em> has a broader appeal and tells an interesting story of a man's conflict, struggle and success.</p><h2>2016 Numbers</h2><p>I read 59 books in 2016 for a total of 22,397 pages. I also read every issue of Amazon's <em>Day One</em> weekly periodical (as I have every year since <em>Day One</em> started being published). Overall my rating distribution is pretty similar to 2015, with my three, four, and five star categories all containing two or three more books than the previous year.</p><h2>Recommendations</h2><p>I awarded twelve books a five star rating. I've listed them below in no particular order. The review links to go my review on Goodreads.</p><ul><li>The Brain Audit: Why Customers Buy (And Why They Don't) (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1534752389'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Charisma Myth - Olivia Fox Cabane (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1047168473'>my review</a>)</li><li>Lying - Sam Harris (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1518371907'>my review</a>)</li><li>To Sell Is Human: The Surprising Truth About Moving Others - Daniel Pink (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/622644583'>my review</a>)</li><li>Climbing Anchors - John Long and Bob Gains (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1484465759'>my review</a>)</li><li>Creativity, Inc. - Ed Catmull and Amy Wallace (<a href='http://www.goodreads.com/review/show/947747190'>my review</a>)</li><li>Chasing the Scream - Johann Hari (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1184643637'>my review</a>)</li><li>Deep Work - Cal Newport (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1529172855'>my review</a>)</li><li>Seveneves - Neal Stephenson (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1295783533'>my review</a>)</li><li>A Little Life - Hanya Yanagihara (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1474596789'>my review</a>)</li><li>The Paper Menagerie and Other Stories - Ken Liu (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1827462108'>my review</a>)</li><li>This Is How You Lose Her - Junot Díaz (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1600396478'>my review</a><a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>)</li></ul><p>While I enjoyed all of the above books, a few stand out.</p><h4><em>Chasing the Scream</em> by Johann Hari</h4><p>This book is about the war on drugs. It brings together studies, history, and anecdotes to present a compelling read on addiction and drug policy. I think it would be hard to finish this book and not be persuaded to vote for policies of drug decriminalization or legalization and more humane addiction treatments. The <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24379960-chasing-the-scream'>goodreads reviews</a> of this book are generally extremely positive, with 61% of them being five stars. Go read the book's summary and a few reviews and you'll want to read this book.</p><h4><em>Deep Work</em> by Cal Newport</h4><p>This book is game changer for those of us that have hobbies or work in fields where distraction-free concentration is beneficial or required. Cal Newport makes the argument that the ability to perform deep work is critical for mastering complicated information and producing great results. The book is split in to two parts. The first defines and makes the argument for deep work. The second prescribes rules for enabling yourself to perform more deep work. I highly recommend reading this book <strong>and</strong> implementing the recommendations<a href='#fn-2' id='fnref2'><sup>2</sup></a>.</p><h4><em>A Little Life</em> by Hanya Yanagihara</h4><p>This is a depressing and challenging book. As <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1167073305?book_show_action=true'>this</a> review says, this book is about a terribly broken character, Jude, and his struggles. The writing is excellent. If you feel up to reading a long, difficult book that exposes you to some terrible experiences then read this book. I'm having a hard time saying this was my favorite fiction book from last year but it is the only five star fiction book I'm specifically calling out.</p><h4><em>Moral Tribes</em> by Joshua Greene</h4><p>I didn't give this book five stars but I'm still going to recommend <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Moral-Tribes-Emotion-Reason-Between/dp/0143126059'>Moral Tribes</a> by Joshua Greene. This book explains how conflict arises when two moral groups meet and interact (an "Us" vs "Them" situation) and proposes Utilitarianism as a solution to this problem. While some parts of the book were a chore to finish, I'm glad I've read this book. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1825978507'>My review</a> highlights more of what I found interesting in this book.</p><p>There is a section of the book that presents both sides of the abortion debate which I've shown to friends on both side of the debate. All of them seemed to enjoy reading this small section of the book.</p><h2>Series read this year</h2><p>I finish almost every book I start reading. I read quick enough where I find it worthwhile to finish marginal books just in case they turn out good. With a book series the end of each book provides a checkpoint for me to reevaluate if I want to continue the series. While none of the below series earned five stars, I'm highlighting them because each series represents me making the choice to continue staying in author's world.</p><p>I continued <a href='https://www.amazon.com/The-Expanse-6-Book-Series/dp/B01J20PMZ6'>The Expanse</a> series this year and read books 4-6. This is just great space opera and I'll continue reading it until it stops being written. </p><p>I started and finished Don Winslow's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/156704-power-of-the-dog'>The Power of the Dog</a> series. It tells the fictionalized tale of drug cartels in Mexico. Parts are brutal and violent and unfortunately often based on real events.</p><p>I read the three main books of Ann Leckie's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/113751-imperial-radch'>Imperial Radch</a>. It is a neat science fiction story that deals with interesting topics. As a warning, I found the first book in the series to be the weakest. Keep pushing and read the second before giving up on this story.</p><p>Scott Meyer's <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/series/131379-magic-2-0'>Magic 2.0</a> was a fun read in which the main character realizes he can edit a file and change reality. It is a silly premise and it delivers good, funny, lighthearted reading.</p><p>I also read Neil Gaiman's <em>American Gods</em> and <em>Anasazi Boys</em>. I devoured both of these books.</p><h2>Technical books read</h2><p>I didn't read many books on software in 2016. I read the lowest number of software related books since I've started keeping track. I finished Ben Rady's <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Serverless-Single-Page-Apps-Available/dp/1680501496'>Serverless Single Page Apps</a> and Ron Jeffries' <a href='https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00VDHRFWU'>The Nature of Software Development</a>. I also read most of Google's Site Reliability Engineering but did not finish it before the end of 2016. I read more non-fiction books than in 2015 but I would have liked to see more software books in the mix.</p><h2>More stats</h2><p>There were definitely a couple months where my reading took a definite dip. I don't remember what I was doing during April or September but apparently I wasn't reading.</p><p><img src="/images/books-and-pages-read-2016.png" alt="Chart of reading per month" title="Chart of reading per month" /></p><p>Unsurprisingly, ebooks continued to be my preferred format. This isn't surprising and I expect that this trend continues. At this point the only reason I'll even potentially look at this stat next year is because it forces me to go through and confirm each book had its format recorded correctly.</p><pre><code>|           | 2014 | 2015 | 2016 |
|-----------+------+------+------|
| ebook     |   64 |   47 |   56 |
| hardcover |    1 |    1 |    0 |
| paperback |    4 |    3 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>My average rating was about the same as 2015.</p><pre><code>| Year | Average Rating |
|------+----------------|
| 2011 |           3.84 |
| 2012 |           3.66 |
| 2013 |           3.67 |
| 2014 |           3.48 |
| 2015 |           3.86 |
| 2016 |           3.83 |
</code></pre><p>I read multiple books by quite a few authors. Below is a table summarizing my repeat</p><pre><code>| Author           | Average Rating | Number of Books | Number of Pages |
|------------------+----------------+-----------------+-----------------|
| Ann Leckie       |          3.667 |               3 |            1205 |
| James S.A. Corey |          3.667 |               3 |            1673 |
| Scott Meyer      |              4 |               3 |            1249 |
| Don Winslow      |              4 |               2 |            1182 |
| Junot Díaz       |              4 |               2 |             565 |
| Michael Crichton |            3.5 |               2 |             814 |
| Neil Gaiman      |              4 |               2 |             981 |
</code></pre><h2>2017 goals</h2><p>This year I'm planning on revisiting some of my favorite books. I'm not going to set a concrete number for this goal and will just have to trust myself to honestly judge if I accomplish this goal.</p><ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>This review is currently blank on Goodreads because this was a book read for a book club I'm part of and we haven't met to discuss the book yet. We typically don't post reviews online of books we'll be discussing. To any of my book club members that are reading this post, I apologize for spoiling the surprise of what star rating I'm planning on giving this book.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-2'>I'm considering writing up more about this book and some changes I've made to help myself do more deep work.<a href='#fnref2'>&#8617;</a></li></ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/03/13/reading-in-2015/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2015]]></title>
    <updated>2016-03-13T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of the year I generally take the time to reflect on my reading in the previous year. I'm nearly three months but I'm finally taking a look at 2015. Here are my summaries of my <a href='http://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/'>2014</a> and <a href='http://jakemccrary.com/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>2013</a> reading.</p><p>I've continued to keep track of my reading by using <a href='http://goodreads.com'>Goodreads</a>. My <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>profile</a> contains the full list and reviews of books I've read since 2010. <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/3431614-jake-mccrary?read_at=2015'>Here</a> is my 2015 list.</p><h3>2015 Goals</h3><p>2015 did not have an easily measured goal. I set the vague goal of increasing the quality of my reading by attempting to think deeper about what I've read.</p><h3>2015 Results</h3><p>I have no idea if I achieved my goal. Some books have stuck with me and I've thought quite a bit about the stories. Others I've forgotten already.</p><p>Looking at raw numbers I read 51 books in 2015 for a total of about 21,790 pages. When compared to 2014 these numbers are lower by 19 books and about 1300 pages.</p><p>In terms of star ratings, 2015 was a better year. I had three more five star books and one more four star book. The 19 book difference between 2014 and 2015 is entirely found in two and three star books.</p><h3>Recommendations</h3><p>I awarded ten books a five star rating. This is more five stars than any other year. Each of the five star books I'd recommend without hesitation. Below is my list of five star books. The <i>my review</i> text links to Goodreads.</p><ul><li>David Foster Wallace - The Pale King (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/882190236'>my review</a>)</li><li>Donna Tartt - The Goldfinch (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1168264855'>my review</a>)</li><li>Donna Tartt - The Secret History (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1225842414'>my review</a>)</li><li>James Clavell - Shogun (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1284160882'>my review</a>)</li><li>John Williams - Stoner (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1152858937'>my review</a>)</li><li>Michael L. Anderson - The Rock Climber's Training Manual (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1420673577'>my review</a>)</li><li>Neal Stephenson - Cryptonomicon (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/799153387'>my review</a>)</li><li>Neal Stephenson - Reamde (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/927872107'>my review</a>)</li><li>Neal Stephenson - Snow Crash (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/799153414'>my review</a>)</li><li>Sam Newman - Building Microservices (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1202873191'>my review</a>)</li></ul><p>One of the great things about writing this post is that it forces me to pause and reflect on the previous years books. Its great seeing this list of great books and remembering the stories. Of these ten books the ones I remember most fondly are <i>Stoner</i>, <i>Snow Crash</i>, and <i>The Pale King</i>.</p><p>There were also a ton of great four star books this year. One that stands out is Joseph Heller's <a href='https://www.amazon.com/SOMETHING-HAPPENED-Joseph-Heller-ebook/dp/B005IQZ894'>Something Happened</a> (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/189671091'>my review</a>). Kurt Vonnegut wrote a brilliant <a href='http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/02/15/home/heller-something.html'>review</a> of this book which I encourage you to read.</p><p>Dave MacLeod's <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Make-Break-Climbing-Injuries-Dictate/dp/0956428134'>Make or Break: Don't Let Climbing Injuries Dictate Your Success</a> (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1236422760'>my review</a>) deserves a mention. I highly recommend this book to any climber. We push our bodies hard and this book will help you prevent and recover from injuries. I've used it as a reference so many times over the past year. It probably deserves five stars.</p><h3>Other Stats</h3><p>Unsurprisingly, I'm continuing to mostly read ebooks.</p><pre><code>|           | 2014 | 2015 |
|-----------+------+------|
| ebook     |   64 |   47 |
| hardcover |    1 |    1 |
| paperback |    4 |    3 |
</code></pre><p>My average rating went up.</p><pre><code>| Year | Average Rating |
|------+----------------|
| 2011 |           3.84 |
| 2012 |           3.66 |
| 2013 |           3.67 |
| 2014 |           3.48 |
| 2015 |           3.86 |
</code></pre><p>Last year I had many repeat authors. This year I had fewer. Neal Stephenson and Donna Tart really stood out this year. I read multiple books from both of them and rated every book five stars.</p><pre><code>| Author               | My Average Rating | Number of Pages | Number of books |
|----------------------+-------------------+-----------------+-----------------|
| Neal Stephenson      |                 5 |            2693 |               3 |
| Donna Tartt          |                 5 |            1427 |               2 |
| Paolo Bacigalupi     |       3.666666667 |            1113 |               3 |
| Bret Easton Ellis    |               3.5 |             590 |               2 |
</code></pre><h3>2016 Goals</h3><p>In 2016 I'm planning on reading one or two biographies. That isn't a genre I typically read. It should be a pretty easy goal to hit. If you have any recommendations please leave them in a comment.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/08/reading-in-2014/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Reading in 2014]]></title>
    <updated>2015-01-08T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of last year I took some time and <a href='http://jakemccrary.com/blog/2014/01/01/using-incanter-to-review-my-2013-reading/'>reviewed</a> my 2013 reading using Clojure and Incanter to generate some stats. It was a useful exercise to reflect back on my reading and play around with Incanter again.</p><p>Over the last couple of weeks I've taken a similar look at my 2014 reading. The rest of this post highlights some of the top books from the previous year and then posts some numbers at the end.</p><p>I review every book I read using <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/'>Goodreads</a>. If you want to see more of what I've been reading you can find me <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/3431614-jake-mccrary'>here</a>. I track and review every book I read and have found this practice to be extremely rewarding.</p><h3>2014 Goals</h3><p>I entered 2014 without a volume goal. Unlike 2013, I didn't have a page or book count goal. I entered 2014 with the desire to reread two specific books and the nebulous goal of reading more non-fiction.</p><h3>2014 Results</h3><p>I ended up setting a new volume record. I read 69 books for a total of almost 23,000 pages. I also read every week of <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00FDWVIHO'>Day One</a>, a weekly literary journal containing one short story and one poem from new authors. This doesn't count towards my page or book count but is reading I enjoy. It exposes me to many different styles.</p><p>More than a third of my reading was non-fiction. I don't have numbers for 2013 but that feels like an increase. I consider my goal of reading more non-fiction achieved.</p><p>I also reread the two books I had planned on rereading. I wanted to reread <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000S1M9LY'>Infinite Jest</a> and <a href='http://www.amazon.com/Hard-Boiled-Wonderland-World-Haruki-Murakami-ebook/dp/B004AP9W1O/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&qid=1420159468&sr=8-1&keywords=a+hard+boiled+wonderland'>Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World</a> and succeeded in rereading both of them.</p><h3>Recommendations</h3><p>I awarded seven books a five out of five star rating. I've listed them below in (in no particular order). Each book I'd recommend without hesitation. Instead of reworking or copying my previous reviews I've provided links to Goodreads. The titles link to Amazon.</p><ul><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00QS2HXUO'>Working Effectively with Unit Tests</a> by Jay Fields (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/984963558'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004J35LHQ'>The Secrets of Consulting</a> by Gerald Weinberg (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/519452572'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00N1ZN6C0'>Extreme Programming Explained</a> by Kent Beck (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1119479193'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000FC1JAI'>Meditations</a> by Marcus Aurelious and translated by Gregory Hays (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/998010207'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000QUELZ4'>A Man Without a Country</a> by Kurt Vonnegut (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/93929432'>my review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000S1M9LY'>Infinite Jest</a> by David Foster Wallace (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/509610965'>my first review</a>, <a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/880349659'>second review</a>)</li><li><a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00IHMF9KE'>The Bone Clocks</a> by David Mitchell (<a href='https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1030027657'>my review</a>)</li></ul><p>I'm recommending a specific translation of <i>Meditations</i>. I attempted to read different one first and it was so painful to read I ended up giving up. The linked translation is modern and contains a useful forward giving you background information on the time.</p><p>I only read one series this year but it was a good one. <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/bookseries/B00HUQBPWE'>The Magicians</a>, by Lev Grossman, was recommended by a friend who described it as "Harry Potter but with characters battling depression." I'm not sure that fully captures the feel of the series but it is a start. The series introduces you to a world like our own but with magic. You follow cynical, self-absorbed students as they attend school, graduate, and grow up living in both the magical and non-magical world. The first book in the series is the weakest so if you read that and find it enjoyable you should definitely pick up the next two books.</p><h3>2015 Goals</h3><p>2015 isn't going to have an easily measured goal. I don't feel the need to set number of books or pages goals any more. I'm hoping to increase the quality of my reading. This is a pretty unclear goal. To me this doesn't mean increasing the average rating of books I read but instead I want to get more out of what I read. I want to think a bit deeper about the subjects I'm reading.</p><h3>2014 Measurements</h3><p>Below are some random measurements that are probably only interesting to me.</p><p>This year I recorded the format of the books I read. This was the year of the ebook; over 90% of the books I read were electronic. I'd guess that this is a higher percentage of ebooks than previous years. I wish I had recorded the formats read in previous years.</p><pre><code>| Binding   | Number of books |
|-----------+-----------------|
| Hardcover |               1 |
| Paperback |               4 |
| Kindle    |              64 |
</code></pre><p>My average rating has been going down over the last four years.</p><pre><code>| Year | Average Rating |
|------+----------------|
| 2011 | 3.84           |
| 2012 | 3.66           |
| 2013 | 3.67           |
| 2014 | 3.48           |
</code></pre><p>In 2014, three authors composed nearly 25% of my reading (by page count). The top six authors by page count are below.</p><pre><code>| Author               | My Average Rating | Number of Books | Number of Pages | Percent of Total Page Count |
|----------------------+-------------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------------------|
| David Mitchell       |                 4 |               5 |            2334 |                      10.19% |
| David Foster Wallace |       4.333333333 |               3 |            1753 |                       7.65% |
| Lev Grossman         |       3.666666667 |               3 |            1244 |                       5.43% |
| Marisha Pessl        |               3.5 |               2 |            1153 |                       5.03% |
| Haruki Murakami      |               3.5 |               2 |             768 |                       3.35% |
| Cormac McCarthy      |               3.5 |               2 |             650 |                       2.84% |
</code></pre><p>My top six authors by average rating (with ties broken by number of books) are below.</p><pre><code>| Author               | My Average Rating | Number of Books | Number of Pages | Percent of Total Page Count |
|----------------------+-------------------+-----------------+-----------------+-----------------------------|
| Gerald M. Weinberg   |                 5 |               1 |             228 |                       1.00% |
| Kent Beck            |                 5 |               1 |             224 |                       0.98% |
| Jay Fields           |                 5 |               1 |             204 |                       0.89% |
| Kurt Vonnegut        |               4.5 |               2 |             377 |                       1.65% |
| David Foster Wallace |       4.333333333 |               3 |            1753 |                       7.65% |
| David Mitchell       |                 4 |               5 |            2334 |                      10.19% |
</code></pre><p>I did top six for both of these because otherwise David Mitchell would not have been in the second one. I've devoured his writing in the last year and a half for a reason. I'm consistently rating his books highly.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
