<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: experiment | Jake McCrary]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/categories/experiment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-09-23T12:50:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Photo Fit]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/07/03/introducing-photo-fit/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-03T18:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/07/03/introducing-photo-fit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this year, I wanted to use a landscape photo as my background on my phone.
It wasn&rsquo;t the photo below but we can use it as an example.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/photo-fit/keyboard-new-keycaps.jpg" title="&ldquo;Landscape image of my keyboard&rdquo; &ldquo;Landscape image of my keyboard&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>When I made it my background, my phone<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> zoomed in to make it fit the portrait orientation of the phone.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/photo-fit/phone-background-before.jpg" title="&ldquo;Screenshot of phone with zoomed in keyboard photo&rdquo; &ldquo;Screenshot of phone with zoomed in keyboard photo&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>This is not great.
I don&rsquo;t want a zoomed in version that fits my vertical phone.
I want to see the whole photo with black bars at the top and bottom</p>

<p>I tried to find a way to add these bars using my phone.
I couldn&rsquo;t find an easy way.</p>

<p>At this point, a reasonable solution would have been transferring the photo to a computer, editing it, and transferring it back to my phone.
I didn&rsquo;t do that.
Instead, I wrote a little TypeScript<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> web app that adds the bars for you.
You open the website on your phone, select an image, and then download a properly sized image.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/photo-fit/phone-background-after.jpg" title="&ldquo;Screenshot of phone with properly fitting image&rdquo; &ldquo;Screenshot of phone with properly fitting image&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>The tool uses the canvas API and does all of the work in the browser itself.
It was a fun, bite-sized project and it gave me an excuse to write some TypeScript and do some web programming.
This was the first time I&rsquo;ve written TypeScript since learning it and I haven&rsquo;t done any web programming in a while.</p>

<p>Making <a href="/experiments/photo-fit/">Photo Fit</a> was not a fast approach to changing my phone&rsquo;s background.
But, now the tool exists and anyone, including future me, can quickly resize their photo from the comfort of their own phone.</p>

<p><a href="/experiments/photo-fit/">Photo Fit</a> is live and available for others to use.
I&rsquo;ve only tested it on my own phone and desktop browsers.
It might not work!
If you do try it and something weird happens, plese let me know.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
A Samsung S8 running Android 9<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></li>
<li id="fn:2">
I recently learned some TypeScript through <a href="https://www.executeprogram.com">Execute Program</a>. Execute program is a really neat application of spaced repetition for learning programming concepts.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
