<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bash | Jake McCrary]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/categories/bash/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-23T22:35:50-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Send a push notification when your external IP address changes]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/05/15/send-a-push-notification-when-your-external-ip-address-changes/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-15T22:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/05/15/send-a-push-notification-when-your-external-ip-address-changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I need to know when my external IP address changes. Whenever it changes, I need to update an IP whitelist and need to re-login to a few sites. I sometimes don&rsquo;t notice for a couple of days and, during that time, some automatic processes fail.</p>

<p>After the last time this happened, I whipped up a script that sends me a push notification when my IP address changes.</p>

<p>The script uses <a href="https://pushover.net/">Pushover</a> to send the push notification. Pushover is great. I have used it for years to get notifications from my headless computers. If you use the below script, replace <code>${PUSHOVER_TOKEN}</code> and <code>${PUSHOVER_USER}</code> with your own details.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">#!/bin/bash

set -e

previous_file="${HOME}/.previous-external-ip"

if [ ! -e "${previous_file}" ]; then
    dig +short myip.opendns.com @resolver1.opendns.com &gt; "${previous_file}"
fi

current_ip=$(dig +short myip.opendns.com @resolver1.opendns.com)

previous_ip=$(cat "${previous_file}")

if [ "${current_ip}" != "${previous_ip}" ]; then
    echo "external ip changed"
    curl -s --form-string "token=${PUSHOVER_TOKEN}" \
         --form-string "user=${PUSHOVER_USER}" \
         --form-string "title=External IP address changed" \
         --form-string "message='${previous_ip}' =&gt; '${current_ip}'" \
         https://api.pushover.net/1/messages.json
fi

echo "${current_ip}" &gt; "${previous_file}"
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better command history in your shell]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/09/28/better-command-history-in-your-shell/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-28T11:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/09/28/better-command-history-in-your-shell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My ideal command history would let me search the history of every
shell but when I hit the up arrow it would only cycle through my
current shell&rsquo;s history. In February, I was able to achieve this setup
in large part because of a utility
called <a href="https://github.com/dvorka/hstr">hstr</a>.</p>

<h2>What is <code>hstr</code>?</h2>

<p>hstr is a neat Bash and Zsh utility that lets you easily search, view,
and manage your command history. hstr provides a tool named <code>hh</code> that
provides a text interface for manipulating your command
history. To see what it looks like check out
the <a href="https://github.com/dvorka/hstr/blob/master/README.md">README</a> and
this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sPF29NyXe2U">video</a> tutorial. If
you are running OS X and use Homebrew you can install it by running <code>brew
install hh</code>.</p>

<h2>Making global history searchable but arrows cycle through local history</h2>

<p>hstr is a neat tool but my favorite part of my setup is how the global
command history is searchable but only a shell&rsquo;s local history is
cycled through with the arrow keys. This is achieved by manipulating
where history is written and tweaking some environment variables.</p>

<p>The first step is to change your <code>$PROMPT_COMMAND</code> to append your
shell&rsquo;s history to a global history file. Below is the snippet that
does this from my <code>.bashrc</code> file.</p>

<pre><code># Whenever a command is executed, write it to a global history
PROMPT_COMMAND="history -a ~/.bash_history.global; $PROMPT_COMMAND"
</code></pre>

<p>The next step is to bind a keystroke to run <code>hh</code>, which is what hstr
provides, with <code>$HISTFILE</code> pointing to <code>~/.bash_history.global</code>. I
wanted to fully replace the default command history searching (and I
use Emacs style keyboard shortcuts) so I&rsquo;ve bound these actions to ctrl-r.</p>

<pre><code class="bash"># On C-r set HISTFILE and run hh
bind -x '"\C-r": "HISTFILE=~/.bash_history.global hh"'
</code></pre>

<p>With those two additions to my <code>.bashrc</code> I&rsquo;ve achieved my ideal
command history searching. When I hit ctrl-r I&rsquo;m searching all of my
history and yet I only cycle through a shell&rsquo;s local history with the
arrow keys. This small addition<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> made my command line productivity
higher.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My setup was inspired by <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/200225/search-history-from-multiple-bash-session-only-when-ctrl-r-is-used-not-when-a">this</a> StackExchange post.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put the last command's run time in your Bash prompt]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/05/03/put-the-last-commands-run-time-in-your-bash-prompt/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T20:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/05/03/put-the-last-commands-run-time-in-your-bash-prompt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m fairly certain the following scenario has happened to every
terminal user. You run a command and, while it is running, realize you
should have prefixed it <a href="http://linux.die.net/man/1/time"><code>time</code></a>. You
momentarily struggle with the thought of killing the command and
rerunning it with <code>time</code>. You decide not to and the command finishes
without you knowing how long it took. You debate running it again.</p>

<p>For the last year I&rsquo;ve lived in a world without this problem. Upon
completion, a command&rsquo;s approximate run time is displayed in my
prompt. It is awesome.</p>

<h2>Overview</h2>

<p>Most of the code below is from a post on
<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/1862762/491871">Stack Overflow</a>. It has
been slightly modified to support having multiple commands in your
<code>$PROMPT_COMMAND</code> variable. Below is a minimal snippet that could be
included in your <code>.bashrc</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">function timer_start {
  timer=${timer:-$SECONDS}
}

function timer_stop {
  timer_show=$(($SECONDS - $timer))
  unset timer
}

trap 'timer_start' DEBUG

if [ "$PROMPT_COMMAND" == "" ]; then
  PROMPT_COMMAND="timer_stop"
else
  PROMPT_COMMAND="$PROMPT_COMMAND; timer_stop"
fi

PS1='[last: ${timer_show}s][\w]$ '
</code></pre>

<p>Modify your <code>.bashrc</code> to include the above and you&rsquo;ll have a prompt
that looks like the image below. It is a minimal prompt but it
includes the time spent on the last command. This is great. No more
wondering how long a command took.</p>

<p><img src="/images/prompt-timings.png" alt="Example of prompt" /></p>

<h2>The details</h2>

<p><code>timer_start</code> is a function that sets <code>timer</code> to be its current value
or, if <code>timer</code> is unset, sets it to the value of <code>$SECONDS</code>.
<code>$SECONDS</code> is a special variable that contains the number of seconds
since the shell was started. <code>timer_start</code> is invoked after every
simple command as a result of <code>trap 'timer_start' DEBUG</code>.</p>

<p><code>timer_stop</code> calculates the difference between <code>$SECONDS</code> and <code>timer</code>
and stores it in <code>timer_show</code>. It also unsets <code>timer</code>. Next time
<code>timer_start</code> is invoked <code>timer</code> will be set to the current value of
<code>$SECONDS</code>. Because <code>timer_stop</code> is part of the <code>$PROMPT_COMMAND</code> it
is executed prior to the prompt being printed.</p>

<p>It is the interaction between <code>timer_start</code> and <code>timer_stop</code> that
captures the run time of commands. It is important that <code>timer_stop</code>
is the <strong>last</strong> command in the <code>$PROMPT_COMMAND</code>. If there are other
commands after it then those will be executed and their execution
might cause <code>timer_start</code> to be called. This results in you timing the
length of time between the prior and current prompts being printed.</p>

<h2>My prompt</h2>

<p>My prompt is a bit more complicated. It shows the last exit code, last
run time, time of day, directory, and git information. The run time of
the last command is one of the more useful parts of my prompt. I
highly recommend you add it to yours.</p>

<p><img src="/images/my-prompt.png" alt="My prompt" /></p>

<h2>Errata</h2>

<p><em>2015/5/04</em></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/gfredericks_">Gary Fredericks</a> noticed that the
original code sample broke if you didn&rsquo;t already have something set as
your <code>$PROMPT_COMMAND</code>. I&rsquo;ve updated the original snippet to reflect
his <a href="https://twitter.com/gfredericks_/status/595249998838800384">changes</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maintaining Directory Layout When Selectively Copying Files]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2013/02/03/maintaining-directory-layout-when-selectively-copying-files/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-03T12:24:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2013/02/03/maintaining-directory-layout-when-selectively-copying-files</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ran into a situation where I needed to replace certain files in a directory tree with files from a similarly shaped directory tree. The other files in each tree needed to remain untouched. Below is an example of the directory structure.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">    root-dir
    ├── target-dir
    │   ├── 20121230
    │   │   ├── data.csv
    │   │   └── instruments.csv
    │   └── 20121231
    │       ├── data.csv
    │       └── instruments.csv
    └── other-dir
        ├── 20121230
        │   ├── data.csv
        │   └── instruments.csv
        └── 20121231
            ├── data.csv
            └── instruments.csv
</code></pre>

<p>Goal is to copy <strong>instruments.csv</strong> from the sub-directories of <strong>other-dir</strong> to the matching sub-directories of <strong>target-dir</strong>. In the past I&rsquo;ve solved this by being in the <strong>other-dir</strong> directory and banging out a <code>for</code> loop at the command line (<code>other-dir$</code> is the bash prompt).</p>

<pre><code class="bash">    other-dir$ for d in $(ls); do cp $d/instruments.txt ../target-dir/$d/; done
</code></pre>

<p>One feature (or issue) with this approach is that if a sub-directory exists in <strong>other-dir</strong> but not in <strong>target-dir</strong> that sub-directory will not be created in <strong>target-dir</strong>.</p>

<p>I took a bit of time to explore other ways of accomplishing this task and stopped after coming up with two additional ways.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">    other-dir$ find . -name "instruments.txt" | xargs -I {} cp {} ../target-dir/{} 
</code></pre>

<p>The above is basically the same as the first solution. It uses <code>find</code> to generate the list of files and then constructs <code>cp</code> commands. It also doesn&rsquo;t create sub-directories in <strong>target-dir</strong>.</p>

<p>The next example has different behavior from the above <code>cp</code> solutions. Like the second solution, it generates a list of files to copy using <code>find</code> but then uses <code>rsync</code> with the <code>--files-from</code> flag to mirror those files under <strong>target-dir</strong>. Unlike the <code>cp</code> based solutions, sub-directories of <strong>other-dir</strong> that do not exist in <strong>target-dir</strong> will be created.</p>

<pre><code>    other-dir$ find . -name "instruments.txt" | rsync --files-from=- . ../target-dir
</code></pre>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure there are many more ways of accomplishing this task. Figuring out the three above was enough for me. They are fairly straight forward and don&rsquo;t depend on esoteric command line flags. The solution I use in the future will depend on whether or not I need sub-directories created in the target directory.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
