<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: onewheel | Jake McCrary]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/categories/onewheel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-29T22:02:48-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Onewheel stand]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2019/08/23/building-a-onewheel-stand/"/>
    <updated>2019-08-23T20:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2019/08/23/building-a-onewheel-stand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve owned a <a href="https://onewheel.com/products/xr">Onewheel XR</a> for about a year now. It is a one-wheeled electric skateboard-like device that is super fun for zipping around Chicago.</p>

<p>When I first got it, I purchased a <a href="https://amzn.to/31Z39Ez">small guitar stand</a>. It worked but it was always a bit finicky and I was never satisfied with it. I had to sit the Onewheel on it just right to have it stay on it without causing the legs of the stand to spread too wide.</p>

<p>This resulted in me buying a <a href="https://amzn.to/2NrrGOI">second guitar stand</a> and trying that out. This one was even worse.</p>

<p>I grew frustrated with these non-purpose built stands and started looking into purchasing a Onewheel stand. There are plenty of beautiful stands out there, both officially from <a href="https://onewheel.com/collections/onewheel-xr-accessories/products/onewheel-deep-shack-rack">Future Motion</a> and from third party vendors like <a href="https://float-supply.com/product-category/stands/">The Float Life</a>.</p>

<p>Then I remembered that my old coworker, Tom Marsh, built his own and put the <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:3682716">plans online</a>. This inspired me to go the DIY route.</p>

<p>I thought that a stand made out of pipe would look pretty good and be easy to construct. It also gave me a good excuse to ride my Onewheel to Home Depot.</p>

<p>I explored the plumbing section of Home Depot and bought a variety of pipe and pipe fittings and took them back home to experiment with putting them together.</p>

<p>I ended up building the stand below.</p>

<p><img src="/images/onewheel-pipe-stand.jpg" title="Onewheel pipe stand" alt="onewheel pipe stand" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/onewheel-in-pipe-stand.png" title="Onewheel in pipe stand" alt="onewheel in pipe stand" /></p>

<p>I think the above stand looks great and it was easy to build.</p>

<p>Here is the part list:</p>

<ul>
<li>2 &frac12; inch x 8 inch nipple</li>
<li>1 &frac12; inch x 6 inch nipple</li>
<li>2 &frac12; inch x 3 inch nipple</li>
<li>2 &frac12; inch 90 degree elbow</li>
<li>2 &frac12; inch 3-way side outlet</li>
<li>2 &frac12; inch cap</li>
</ul>


<p>I washed off the black coating using Goo Gone and then assembled the stand. This ups the risk of rust but I think that might actually look cool so I&rsquo;m not too worried about it. You could optionally coat the pipes for some protection.</p>

<p>Once you have the parts the assembly is very straight forward. The only additional work I might do is to put some rubber feet on the bottom to prevent scratches to my floor.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
