<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Jake McCrary's articles on meetings]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-03T01:14:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/16/a-retrospective-format/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/16/a-retrospective-format/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[A retrospective format for remote or co-located teams]]></title>
    <updated>2020-03-16T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p><a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=Agile_Retrospective_Resource_Wiki'>Retrospectives</a> are a useful type of meeting to have periodically with your team. There are many different <a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=Retrospective_Plans'>formats</a> of retrospectives.</p><p>One of them can be summarized in the following steps:</p><ol><li>Gather the team together</li><li>Set the stage</li><li>Brainstorm answers to the questions <code>What went well?</code> and <code>What needs improvement?</code></li><li>Discuss the answers</li></ol><p>Let's talk about each step and see how each works with an co-located or remote team.</p><h3>Step 1: Gather the team</h3><p>This step is self explanatory. If you are an in-person team, then this is gathering everyone together in a room for some allotted about of time. If you are a remote team, or have remote folks on your team, then this is gathering everyone together in a video conference.</p><p>Preferably everyone in the retro is communicating in same way. This means if <strong>anyone</strong> is remote, it is preferable that <strong>everyone</strong> join the video conference from their own computer instead of using a single screen and video from a shared conference room. My earlier article about <a href='/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/'>tips for remote meetings</a> goes into more details on this topic.</p><p>Everyone using the same communication method puts everyone on the same page and dramatically improves the experience for the remote folks. With a mixed group, we'll want to use some remote collaboration tools anyway, so it is useful for everyone to have their own computer with them. They might as well use it for video communication as well.</p><h3>Step 2: Set the stage</h3><p>This part doesn't differ between an entirely in-person meeting, mixed, or entirely remote meeting.</p><p>Take the time to set the stage for the meeting. Remind everyone that we're here to improve and to listen with an open mind. Remind everyone to try to not make things personal and not take things personally. This is a good time to read the <a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive'>Prime Directive</a>.</p><p>This is also a good time to set the boundaries of the discussion. What is the retrospective covering? Is it covering the last few weeks? The last quarter? The new working from home experience? Pick a topic so everyone in the meeting focuses on the same things.</p><h3>Step 3: Answer the questions</h3><p>In this step, we will answer the questions <code>What went well?</code> and <code>What needs improvement?</code> and use those answers for discussion in the remainder of the meeting. Timebox this step to 5 to 10 minutes.</p><p>In an in-person setting, this is often done through the use of <a href='https://www.post-it.com/3M/en_US/post-it/products/~/Post-it-Products/Notes/Super-Sticky/?N=4327+5927575+7568222+3294529207+3294857497&rt=r3'>Post-it</a> notes. Give each attendee a marker and a stack of notes and have each person write down as many answers as they can come up with, one per post-it note, to the two questions. Dedicate a section of a whiteboard or wall for each question and have people bring the generated answers to the respective sections. Try to group the answers by topics.</p><p>With a remote meeting, you don't have the physical whiteboard and cards. That is perfectly fine! Once you figure out your remote collaboration tools, this part of the retrospective isn't difficult.</p><p>I've mostly done remote retrospectives using <a href='https://trello.com/'>Trello</a>. Trello works great for this as it is multi-user and does a great job of presenting lists to a group. Here is how previous teams I've worked with setup Trello for remote retrospectives.</p><p>First, make a Trello board and make sure everyone has an invite to view and edit the board. Second, add the following columns to the board.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/retros-first-three-columns.png" alt="First three columns before any cards" title="First three columns before any cards" /></p><p>The first column is for Step 2 of the process and is there to remind everyone why we're all spending time in this meeting.</p><p>Columns two and three are used in this step. Have attendees add cards to these columns as they come up with answers If anyone notices duplicates during this time frame, move them near each other by dragging them up or down in the column. If you notice someone else has already put a card that you'd put up there, don't bother putting it down again (this differs from the in-person meeting).</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-before-voting.png" alt="First three columns with cards before voting" /></p><h4>[remote only] Step 3.5: Vote on cards</h4><p>This step sneaks into the remote retrospective and is missing from the in-person retro. In the in-person retro, duplication of post-it notes serves as this voting stage.</p><p>Once all the answers have been generated, or time is up, it is time to vote on what will be discussed in the next step. Only have people vote on the <code>What needs improvement?</code> answers.</p><p>There are at least two ways of doing this in Trello but my favorite is having attendees hover their mouse cursor over the card and then hit <code>space bar</code><a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>. This sticks their avatar on the card (in Trello speak, I believe this is called joining a card). You can either restrict folks to a certain number of votes, say 3, or let them go wild and vote as many times as they want. I haven't found the outcomes to be much different and find infinite votes more fun.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-columns-with-votes.png" alt="First three columns with votes" /></p><p>Once voting is finished (again, timer or when it seems to have reached an end), have one person sort the cards by number of votes with the highest votes at the top of the list.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-columns-votes-sorted.png" alt="First three columns with cards sorted by votes" /></p><h3>Step 4: Discuss the answers</h3><p>With in-person or remote retros, go over the answers to <code>What went well?</code> first. This starts the discussion with positive feelings. This part usually goes pretty fast as we're just celebrating wins and not having a long discussions about them.</p><p>Next, start discussing the answers to <code>What needs improvement?</code></p><p>For each topic being discussed, set a five minute timer. At the end of the five minutes, do a quick poll of the attendees on if the topic should be continued or not. If it should be continued, start a three minute timer and continue discussion. At the end of those three minutes, repeat the vote for continuing or not.</p><p>Throughout the discussion, try to be mindful of people dominating conversation and give everyone a chance to voice their thoughts. Try to figure out some next steps to take to actually start making improvements on what needs to be improved.</p><p>The above is generic advice for remote or in-person retros. When you're running a remote retro using Trello, it can be useful to do the following as well.</p><p>You should add two more columns, <code>Next Steps</code> and <code>Discussed</code>, to the right of the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/last-three-columns-before-discussion.png" alt="Additional columns added to board" /></p><p>Since your cards are sorted in the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column, you'll always be talking about the top card. As discussion finishes, move it from the top of the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column into the <code>Discussed</code> column. As <code>Next Steps</code> are discovered, add cards to the <code>Next Steps</code> column and assign the people responsible for following up to the card. Below is an example of those three columns after discussing two cards.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/final-three-columns-post-discussion.png" alt="Final state of last three columns" /></p><p>When voting on continuing discussion or not, it can be useful to have a hand signal for taking the vote and for continuing or ending the discussion. We'd do a quick thumbs up or thumbs down and if half the team wants to keep going then we'd seamlessly start the next timer.</p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>Retrospectives can be a very handy tool for a team's continuous improvement. If time isn't provided for reflecting, then reflecting does not happen and this makes improving harder.</p><p>Remote retrospectives provide a challenge since most of us only have experience using physical sticky notes or whiteboards for collecting answers. We don't need to recreate the same form factor for remote retrospectives. Using remote collaboration tools, such as Trello, that don't recreate the sticky-note-on-wall experience can lead to initial confusion but, once familiar with them, the experience is pleasant and allows for greater participation.</p><p>How is participation increased? Well, in an in-person retrospective you often are unable to read what everyone else has stuck up on the wall because of physical distance. With a remote retro, you're able to read every answer added to the lists.</p><p>Don't be afraid of running a remote retrospective. They can be incredibly useful. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>The alternative method I'm aware of is to use a Trello Power-up to enable voting on cards. But why bother doing this when you can just stick faces on cards.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[7 tips for a successful remote meeting]]></title>
    <updated>2016-06-28T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>As mentioned in my <a href='/blog/2016/06/14/tips-for-working-from-home/'>tips for working from home</a> article, I've been working remotely for nearly three years. In those three years I've been in countless meetings, both productive and unproductive. Meetings, both in-person and remote, are hard. Remote meetings pose some additional challenges but they also offer some unique benefits.</p><p>Below are seven tips that will help you have successful remote meetings. I wrote this article focusing on remote meetings but many of these tips will improve your co-located meetings as well.</p><h3>Have an agenda</h3><p>If you are organizing a meeting, you should make sure that the meeting has an agenda. The agenda doesn't have to be a long, complicated document; it can be as simple as a list of topics and goals.</p><p>Why should you have an agenda? An agenda helps focus discussion by providing an outline of what the meeting is designed to cover.</p><p>Send out your agenda with the meeting invite. This gives invitees time to think about the topics and helps prevent people from showing up clueless. It also provides an opportunity for an invitee to excuse themself or suggest an alternative person if they don't believe they will contribute to the meeting.</p><h3>Start and end on time</h3><p>You should start your meetings on time. You should end your meetings on time or early. If you are not starting and ending on time then you are not being respectful of your attendees time. The lack of punctuality contributes towards people dreading meetings.</p><p>If you are running out of time, wind down the meeting. If more discussions need to happen, reflect and see if more time needs to be scheduled with the entire group or if only a subset of the group is required.</p><h3>Use video chat</h3><p>Even if you don't work remotely, you've probably had to dial in to a group audio chat. This is almost always a terrible experience. Without body language, it is near impossible to tell when someone is about to start speaking and, as a result, there are awkward pauses while everyone waits for someone else to speak and everyone speaks over each other. It is terrible.</p><p>This is why I recommend using video chat. Video chats let you see the other people on the call and this allows you to pick up on physical cues. These cues vastly improve communication in the meeting.</p><h3>Co-located attendees should use their own device</h3><p>Sometimes you'll have a mixed meeting, some attendees are remote and others are together in an office. The co-located attendees should each use their own device to connect to the meeting.</p><p>Co-located attendees sharing a single device is non-optimal for many reasons. It is often hard for all the co-located attendees to be captured by the camera in a way that enables the remote attendees to reliably view them. Sharing a single microphone also makes it so some co-located attendees are easy to hear and others are barely audible.</p><p>Using a single device also makes it harder for all the co-located attendees to view the remote attendees. Without a clear view of the remote attendees, the co-located attendees often accidentally exclude the remote people by focusing on discussions between the co-located group.</p><h3>Ignore distractions</h3><p>Hopefully you have invited just the right people to the meeting and everyone is engaged in the discussion and paying attention. Realistically this doesn't happen. Computers are incredibly good at so many things and one of those things is distracting the user.</p><p>When you are attending a remote meeting, minimize what can distract you. Close your email and hide the chat program. Put your phone out of arms reach. Try to focus intently on the meeting. If you find yourself not paying attention and not contributing, take this as a signal that you shouldn't be in this meeting. If nothing on the rest of the agenda seems like it requires you, then leave the meeting and be more selective about what you join in the future.</p><p>If you notice other attendees not paying attention, gently call them out on it. This can be done by soliciting discussion from them or by being direct.  </p><h3>Have a shared artifact</h3><p>This is one of the more important tips in this list and it is one of the areas where remote meetings have an advantage over in-person meetings.</p><p>When the meeting starts give everyone a link to a shared document that everyone can edit (for example a <a href='https://www.google.com/docs/about/'>Google Doc</a>). It can be useful to seed this document with the agenda. This shared document can be used to capture whatever you want. I've found it useful to capture options discussed, pros/cons lists, and follow-up actions. Writing in the shared document helps solidify ideas and gives the group a reference both during and after the meeting.</p><p>With in-person meetings, this shared artifact is often a whiteboard. Whiteboards are immensely useful but are barely editable by more than one person at once and are harder to reference after a meeting. I know I'm not the only person who dislikes trying to decipher terrible whiteboard handwriting captured by someone's phone.</p><p>Except for when drawing diagrams, I've found the Google Docs style shared document used during a remote meeting more effective than using a whiteboard in an in-person meeting. You can always use a shared document in an in-person meeting as well but then you are requiring attendees to have a laptop open and that is an invitation for distracted attendees.</p><h3>Assign responsibilities</h3><p>Hopefully you are having a meeting to influence an outcome and not just hear everyone talk. As a result, you should be assigning follow-up responsibilities as the meeting progresses. Make the follow-up actions explicit and assigned to an individual. You can capture these responsibilities in your shared artifact.<h2></h2></p><p>Meetings can be difficult. You should do what you can to make them more successful. If you are being invited to a meeting without an agenda, ask for an agenda. If you're in a meeting and you can tell someone is constantly distracted, try nicely calling them out on it (either privately or in the group). If there isn't a shared artifact, make one and suggest it to the group. Meetings don't have to be terrible. We can make them better.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
