<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: windows | Jake McCrary]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/categories/windows/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-11-19T18:52:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manage your workspace with grids under Linux, OS X, and Windows]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2013/04/15/manage-your-workspace-with-grids-under-linux-osx-and-windows/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-15T19:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2013/04/15/manage-your-workspace-with-grids-under-linux-osx-and-windows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m the type of computer user that wants an organized
workspace. To me this means having my active applications organized
into a grid. Efficiently doing this is important to me. Before I jump
into what tools I use let me give a quick explanation of what
organized into a grid means to me.</p>

<p>Imagine that your screen is divided both vertically and
horizontally. To me a good tool for managing windows lets you take
your active application and move it so it fits in any rectangle formed
by the edges of your screen and those two lines splitting your
monitor. This means that with a keystroke you can make the active
window take up the full screen, half screen, or quarter screen. Below
I&rsquo;ve listed the tools that let me do that.</p>

<h4>Linux</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;ve switched to using <a href="http://i3wm.org/">i3</a>, a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiling_window_manager">tiling window manager</a>
instead of the default window manager on every distribution I use. When using
i3 the tiling is done automatically. There are hotkeys for changing
window layout and for moving focus between windows. The automatic tiling and
shortcuts take a bit to get used to, but now that I am I can&rsquo;t believe
I switched to using a tiling window manager sometime in the last eight
months.</p>

<h4>Windows</h4>

<p>When developing under Windows I use
<a href="http://winsplit-revolution.com/">Winsplit Revolution</a>. Unlike i3,
Winsplit Revolution only provides hotkeys snapping windows to
different locations. This is admittedly more approachable than i3 as
the grid isn&rsquo;t forced on you. WinSplit Revolution is pretty flexible,
you can change shortcuts and even define your own grid.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t remember when I started using Winsplit Revolution but it has
become a vital tool for when I&rsquo;m stuck doing development on a Windows
machine.</p>

<h4>OS X</h4>

<p>My only OS X machine is my 13 inch MacBook Air. I always thought that
with such a small screen being able to tile my windows wouldn&rsquo;t be as
useful. I  was completely wrong. If anything it may be more useful
because of the tiny screen real estate. The 13 inch screen is just wide
enough to have an editor up on one half and documentation on the
other.</p>

<p>The tool I use to snap my windows to a grid is
<a href="http://spectacleapp.com/">Spectacle</a>. Spectacle provides some
sensible keystrokes for moving windows around. The hotkeys are
similar to Winsplit Revolution&rsquo;s which makes switching between
operating systems easy.</p>

<p>If you haven&rsquo;t tried using a tool to help you organize your windows I
highly recommend that you do. I&rsquo;ve introduced both technical and
non-technical people to these tools and everyone has enjoyed them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
