<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | Jake McCrary]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2024-02-18T18:21:12-06:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bookmarklets on mobile are useful]]></title>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2022/11/13/bookmarklets-on-mobile-are-useful/"/>
    <updated>2022-11-13T18:36:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2022/11/13/bookmarklets-on-mobile-are-useful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bookmarklets, little snippets of JavaScript that you keep around as a bookmark, are useful.
They let you execute some JavaScript to perform almost any action you want on a website.</p>

<p>Some bookmarklets I use on my desktop browser include:</p>

<ol>
<li>A collection of bookmarklets that let you change the playback speed of most embedded videos.</li>
<li>A bookmarklet to manipulate the URL of the page you&rsquo;re visiting.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://pinboard.in/howto/">bookmarklet</a> to save the current page&rsquo;s URL to pinboard.in.</li>
</ol>


<p>For years, I thought I was restricted to only using bookmarklets in my desktop web browser.
I hadn&rsquo;t effectively used mobile bookmarks before and thought that clicking them would be a huge pain.</p>

<p>It turns out, I was wrong!
I recently learned that if you start typing a bookmark&rsquo;s title into your mobile browser&rsquo;s location bar, it will let you select the bookmark.
This means you can easily execute a bookmarklet just by starting to type its name and clicking it when it appears.
This &ldquo;search for bookmark in location bar&rdquo; technique works with at least Google Chrome and Brave running in Android.</p>

<p>Below are the two bookmarklets I use regularly on my phone.
They exist to bypass paywalls.</p>

<p>This one prepends <code>http://archive.is/</code> to the current URL:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">javascript:(function() {window.location="http://archive.is/"+window.location.toString();}())
</code></pre>

<p>This one changes <code>theatlantic.com</code> to <code>theatlantic.com.</code> (though it no longer gets around their paywall):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">javascript:(function() {window.location=window.location.href.replace(/theatlantic.com/, 'theatlantic.com.');}())
</code></pre>

<p>To get them onto my phone, I added them a bookmarks on my laptop&rsquo;s Chrome and synced them to my mobile phone.
Once in my mobile Chrome, I edited the bookmark in mobile Chrome, copied the code, and pasted it into a bookmark in Brave.</p>

<p>I type three characters into my mobile browser&rsquo;s location bar before I can select either of these bookmarklets.
That is quicker than editing the URLs by hand and has improved the experience of reading articles on my phone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
