<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Jake McCrary's articles on tmate]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-03T01:14:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/04/12/making-tmate-and-tmux-play-nice-with-os-x-terminal-notifier/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/04/12/making-tmate-and-tmux-play-nice-with-os-x-terminal-notifier/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Making tmate and tmux play nice with OS X terminal-notifier]]></title>
    <updated>2015-04-12T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For nearly the last two years, I've been doing most of my development in OS X. Most of that development has been done in Clojure and, whenever possible, using <a href='https://github.com/jakemcc/lein-test-refresh'>lein-test-refresh</a> with <a href='https://github.com/alloy/terminal-notifier'>terminal-notifier</a> to have my tests automatically run and a notification shown with the status of the test run. Its a great work flow that gives me a quick feedback cycle and doesn't pull my attention in different directions.</p><p>Recently I've started using <a href='http://tmate.io/'>tmate</a> for remote pairing. Unfortunately when I first started using it my quick feedback cycle was broken. <code>lein test-refresh</code> would run my tests but would become hung when sending a notification using <code>terminal-notifier</code>. This was terrible and, if I hadn't been able to fix it, would have stopped me from using <code>tmate</code>. After some searching I stumbled across <a href='https://github.com/alloy/terminal-notifier/issues/115'>this</a> GitHub issue which helped solve the problem.</p><p>To make <code>tmate</code> work nicely with <code>terminal-notifier</code> you'll need to install <a href='https://github.com/ChrisJohnsen/tmux-MacOSX-pasteboard'>reattach-to-user-namespace</a> and change your <code>tmate</code> configuration to use it. If you use <code>brew</code> you can install by running `brew install &ndash;with-wrap-pbcopy-and-pbpaste reattach-to-user-namespace<code>. Then open your </code>.tmux.conf` or <code>.tmate.conf</code> file and add the line below.</p><pre><code>set-option -g default-command &quot;which reattach-to-user-namespace &gt; /dev/null &amp;&amp; reattach-to-user-namespace -l $SHELL || $SHELL&quot;
</code></pre><p>The above tells <code>tmate</code> to use <code>reattach-to-user-namespace</code> if it is available. Now <code>terminal-notifier</code> no longer hangs when invoked inside <code>tmate</code>. Unsurprisingly, this change also makes <code>tmux</code> place nice with <code>terminal-notifier</code>.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
