<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Jake McCrary's articles on remote]]></title>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-02-03T00:51:56+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://jakemccrary.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake McCrary]]></name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/16/a-retrospective-format/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/16/a-retrospective-format/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[A retrospective format for remote or co-located teams]]></title>
    <updated>2020-03-16T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p><a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=Agile_Retrospective_Resource_Wiki'>Retrospectives</a> are a useful type of meeting to have periodically with your team. There are many different <a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=Retrospective_Plans'>formats</a> of retrospectives.</p><p>One of them can be summarized in the following steps:</p><ol><li>Gather the team together</li><li>Set the stage</li><li>Brainstorm answers to the questions <code>What went well?</code> and <code>What needs improvement?</code></li><li>Discuss the answers</li></ol><p>Let's talk about each step and see how each works with an co-located or remote team.</p><h3>Step 1: Gather the team</h3><p>This step is self explanatory. If you are an in-person team, then this is gathering everyone together in a room for some allotted about of time. If you are a remote team, or have remote folks on your team, then this is gathering everyone together in a video conference.</p><p>Preferably everyone in the retro is communicating in same way. This means if <strong>anyone</strong> is remote, it is preferable that <strong>everyone</strong> join the video conference from their own computer instead of using a single screen and video from a shared conference room. My earlier article about <a href='/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/'>tips for remote meetings</a> goes into more details on this topic.</p><p>Everyone using the same communication method puts everyone on the same page and dramatically improves the experience for the remote folks. With a mixed group, we'll want to use some remote collaboration tools anyway, so it is useful for everyone to have their own computer with them. They might as well use it for video communication as well.</p><h3>Step 2: Set the stage</h3><p>This part doesn't differ between an entirely in-person meeting, mixed, or entirely remote meeting.</p><p>Take the time to set the stage for the meeting. Remind everyone that we're here to improve and to listen with an open mind. Remind everyone to try to not make things personal and not take things personally. This is a good time to read the <a href='https://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive'>Prime Directive</a>.</p><p>This is also a good time to set the boundaries of the discussion. What is the retrospective covering? Is it covering the last few weeks? The last quarter? The new working from home experience? Pick a topic so everyone in the meeting focuses on the same things.</p><h3>Step 3: Answer the questions</h3><p>In this step, we will answer the questions <code>What went well?</code> and <code>What needs improvement?</code> and use those answers for discussion in the remainder of the meeting. Timebox this step to 5 to 10 minutes.</p><p>In an in-person setting, this is often done through the use of <a href='https://www.post-it.com/3M/en_US/post-it/products/~/Post-it-Products/Notes/Super-Sticky/?N=4327+5927575+7568222+3294529207+3294857497&rt=r3'>Post-it</a> notes. Give each attendee a marker and a stack of notes and have each person write down as many answers as they can come up with, one per post-it note, to the two questions. Dedicate a section of a whiteboard or wall for each question and have people bring the generated answers to the respective sections. Try to group the answers by topics.</p><p>With a remote meeting, you don't have the physical whiteboard and cards. That is perfectly fine! Once you figure out your remote collaboration tools, this part of the retrospective isn't difficult.</p><p>I've mostly done remote retrospectives using <a href='https://trello.com/'>Trello</a>. Trello works great for this as it is multi-user and does a great job of presenting lists to a group. Here is how previous teams I've worked with setup Trello for remote retrospectives.</p><p>First, make a Trello board and make sure everyone has an invite to view and edit the board. Second, add the following columns to the board.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/retros-first-three-columns.png" alt="First three columns before any cards" title="First three columns before any cards" /></p><p>The first column is for Step 2 of the process and is there to remind everyone why we're all spending time in this meeting.</p><p>Columns two and three are used in this step. Have attendees add cards to these columns as they come up with answers If anyone notices duplicates during this time frame, move them near each other by dragging them up or down in the column. If you notice someone else has already put a card that you'd put up there, don't bother putting it down again (this differs from the in-person meeting).</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-before-voting.png" alt="First three columns with cards before voting" /></p><h4>[remote only] Step 3.5: Vote on cards</h4><p>This step sneaks into the remote retrospective and is missing from the in-person retro. In the in-person retro, duplication of post-it notes serves as this voting stage.</p><p>Once all the answers have been generated, or time is up, it is time to vote on what will be discussed in the next step. Only have people vote on the <code>What needs improvement?</code> answers.</p><p>There are at least two ways of doing this in Trello but my favorite is having attendees hover their mouse cursor over the card and then hit <code>space bar</code><a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>. This sticks their avatar on the card (in Trello speak, I believe this is called joining a card). You can either restrict folks to a certain number of votes, say 3, or let them go wild and vote as many times as they want. I haven't found the outcomes to be much different and find infinite votes more fun.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-columns-with-votes.png" alt="First three columns with votes" /></p><p>Once voting is finished (again, timer or when it seems to have reached an end), have one person sort the cards by number of votes with the highest votes at the top of the list.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/first-three-columns-votes-sorted.png" alt="First three columns with cards sorted by votes" /></p><h3>Step 4: Discuss the answers</h3><p>With in-person or remote retros, go over the answers to <code>What went well?</code> first. This starts the discussion with positive feelings. This part usually goes pretty fast as we're just celebrating wins and not having a long discussions about them.</p><p>Next, start discussing the answers to <code>What needs improvement?</code></p><p>For each topic being discussed, set a five minute timer. At the end of the five minutes, do a quick poll of the attendees on if the topic should be continued or not. If it should be continued, start a three minute timer and continue discussion. At the end of those three minutes, repeat the vote for continuing or not.</p><p>Throughout the discussion, try to be mindful of people dominating conversation and give everyone a chance to voice their thoughts. Try to figure out some next steps to take to actually start making improvements on what needs to be improved.</p><p>The above is generic advice for remote or in-person retros. When you're running a remote retro using Trello, it can be useful to do the following as well.</p><p>You should add two more columns, <code>Next Steps</code> and <code>Discussed</code>, to the right of the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/last-three-columns-before-discussion.png" alt="Additional columns added to board" /></p><p>Since your cards are sorted in the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column, you'll always be talking about the top card. As discussion finishes, move it from the top of the <code>What needs improvement?</code> column into the <code>Discussed</code> column. As <code>Next Steps</code> are discovered, add cards to the <code>Next Steps</code> column and assign the people responsible for following up to the card. Below is an example of those three columns after discussing two cards.</p><p><img src="/images/remote-retros/final-three-columns-post-discussion.png" alt="Final state of last three columns" /></p><p>When voting on continuing discussion or not, it can be useful to have a hand signal for taking the vote and for continuing or ending the discussion. We'd do a quick thumbs up or thumbs down and if half the team wants to keep going then we'd seamlessly start the next timer.</p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>Retrospectives can be a very handy tool for a team's continuous improvement. If time isn't provided for reflecting, then reflecting does not happen and this makes improving harder.</p><p>Remote retrospectives provide a challenge since most of us only have experience using physical sticky notes or whiteboards for collecting answers. We don't need to recreate the same form factor for remote retrospectives. Using remote collaboration tools, such as Trello, that don't recreate the sticky-note-on-wall experience can lead to initial confusion but, once familiar with them, the experience is pleasant and allows for greater participation.</p><p>How is participation increased? Well, in an in-person retrospective you often are unable to read what everyone else has stuck up on the wall because of physical distance. With a remote retro, you're able to read every answer added to the lists.</p><p>Don't be afraid of running a remote retrospective. They can be incredibly useful. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>The alternative method I'm aware of is to use a Trello Power-up to enable voting on cards. But why bother doing this when you can just stick faces on cards.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/10/more-working-from-home-tips/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2020/03/10/more-working-from-home-tips/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[More working from home tips]]></title>
    <updated>2020-03-10T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>With the the new coronavirus spreading through the world, more people are either choosing or are being forced to work from home. From 2013 to 2018, the companies I worked for were entirely remote. For the rest of my professional career, 2007 to 2013 and 2018 to now (March 2020), I've also frequently worked from home.</p><p>I've managed to be very effective at it and I think others can be as well.</p><p>After years of working in an office, transitioning to working from home isn't easy. I had difficulty with the transition and people I've mentored have as well. I think most people will be able to be effective at home, assuming their workplace is supportive, if they try to get better at it. With a supportive company or team, once you get used to working from home you probably find yourself getting more done.</p><p>The key word in the sentence "I'm working from home" is <strong>working</strong>. You are going to be <strong>working</strong> where you spend a lot of your non-work time. This can be a difficult mental transition. Physically switching to an office environment can help switch your brain into work mode and now you no longer have that. Don't worry, it might feel rough in the beginning but you will get better at it.</p><p>I've written more articles about working <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>remotely</a> and I'd recommend you read those as well. This article is primarily targeted at the person not making a permanent change in their work from home status. My <a href='/blog/2017/10/31/a-guide-to-distributed-work/'>Guide to Distributed Work</a> is a bit more targeted at someone that is permanently choosing to work at home or in a position of power to influence work from home policies at a company. I'd recommend that you read it as well as many of the subjects it talks about are generally applicable. It steps through some of the pros and cons of remote work and links to other writing on the topic.</p><p>Below is a hodgepodge of tips for working from home.</p><h3>Setup a home workspace</h3><p>In my years of remote work, I've always managed to have a <a href='/blog/2015/03/31/my-home-work-space/'>dedicated space</a> for work. In some apartments, this was a corner of a room where I put a desk and faced a wall. In other apartments, I've been privileged enough to have a dedicated room for an office.</p><p>If you aren't planning on working from home permanently, or very frequently, then you probably don't want to spend a significant amount of money setting up a work area. This probably means you don't want to find a home with a dedicated office and you may not want or be able to dedicate a portion of a room to a desk<a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>.</p><p>Whatever your living arrangement is, I'd encourage you to figure a way to have a regular spot to work at while you are working. Having a regular spot to work from will help your brain turn on and off from work mode.</p><p>Setting up a home workspace can be as low cost as using a <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Folding-Holder-Height-Adjustments-Original/dp/B01LZPMFW9/'>tv tray</a> or <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Lifetime-80251-Adjustable-Folding-Granite/dp/B0074HYWFG/'>folding table</a><a href='#fn-2' id='fnref2'><sup>2</sup></a> with a chair. Your setup could be as elaborate as getting a height adjustable desk with large monitors. It could be something else entirely.</p><p>Find something that works for you and stick with it.</p><p>Beyond a dedicated space to work, make sure you have a reliable internet connection. If you can, use Ethernet as it is generally better than WiFi. I've never had a situation where I could use Ethernet and have found that having a good router is enough to make my WiFi reliable.</p><h3>Discuss boundaries and expectations with your cohabitants</h3><p>If you live with others that will be at home while you need to work, you should have a discussion with them about boundaries. You are at home to do work and that expectation needs to be set. You may be able to do some household chores during breaks or take other breaks with cohabitants but everyone in your living area needs to understand you are at home to work.</p><p>If you have children that might have a particularly hard time with this, it can be useful to use some sort of physical signaling device (examples: a closed door, a light bulb being on, a closed curtain, headphones on) that you should not be interrupted.</p><h3>Minimize distractions</h3><p>This one is obvious but try to minimize distractions. Don't try to sit on your couch with the TV on and do work. You won't be doing great work.</p><p>If your home is loud and you have difficulty in a loud space, wear some ear plugs or noise canceling headphones.</p><p>If cohabitants are distractions, refer to the above section and have that discussion with them about needing space. One technique for dealing with interrupting cohabitants is to schedule time throughout your day for them. You can use these scheduled times as breaks through out your working day.</p><p>If you try to get some household chores done while working at home, make sure you schedule time for doing them. This could be putting the time on your calendar or simply setting a timer when taking a break. Regardless of the method, when your time is up, get back to work.</p><p>I've often found that finishing a short, simple household task can actually jump-start finishing more complicated work tasks. Using that momentum from the household chore can make accomplishing work tasks easier.</p><h3>Having difficulty starting a work task?</h3><p>Sometimes it is hard to start a task. It can be especially hard if you are new to working at home and not used to working in your environment.</p><p>One technique I've found useful is the Pomodoro technique. The steps to this technique are below.</p><ol><li>Pick a task.</li><li>Set and start a timer (usually for 25 minutes).</li><li>Focus intensely on the task for the duration of the timer.</li><li>Make a mark on a piece of paper</li><li>If you have fewer than four marks on the paper, take a 5 minute break and then go back to step 2.</li><li>If you have four marks on the paper, then take a 15 minute break and go back to step 1.</li></ol><p>I don't follow those steps strictly and mostly use the trick of setting a timer for focused work. If at the end of the timer I feel like continuing, I'll reset the timer. If I need a break, I'll set the timer for a short period of time and take a break.</p><p>It was mentioned above, but sometimes doing a small, easy task can jump-start knocking out TODOs. This small, easy task could be something work related or some simple chore around the house.</p><h3>Be mindful of your communication</h3><p>Text communication is hard. It is often taken more negative than intended. Be mindful of that.</p><p>Try to take what your coworkers write in the most positive way possible.</p><p>Try to be careful with your own written communication. It sounds ridiculous but emojis can help make you look like less of a jerk and set a friendly tone.</p><p>Don't hesitate to jump on a video or voice call with someone (or a group). Video is a much higher quality interaction than voice and both are much higher quality than text. The downside is the communication isn't persistent so be sure to write down outcomes of conversations.</p><h3>Sync up with your team</h3><p>Try to sync up with your team (if you don't have a team, sync up with someone else from the company) at a regular interval. This should probably be at least once every couple days but it can be more regularly. I usually once a day.</p><p>It can be easy to feel like an island when you are part of a remote group. Regular sync-ups help reduce that feeling.</p><h3>Collaborate remotely</h3><p>Most video conference software allows you to share your screen with others. Some of them even allow others to take control of your machine or treat your screen as a whiteboard.</p><p>Take advantage of these features. After learning how to use them, these features can often make remote collaboration as productive as in-person collaboration.</p><p>Using technology, you can even <a href='/blog/2015/01/24/remote-pairing/'>pair program</a> with someone from another city.</p><p>Google Docs is another great remote collaboration tool. The best meetings I have been part of were meetings where every attendee was editing a shared Google Doc.</p><h3>Video Meetings</h3><p>When possible, have video meetings over voice only conference calls. The addition of body language through video makes remote conversations much better.</p><p>You might want to introduce hand gestures for signaling during video meetings<a href='#fn-3' id='fnref3'><sup>3</sup></a>. On a former team, we had the practice of raising a finger<a href='#fn-4' id='fnref4'><sup>4</sup></a> when you wanted to speak. This practice helped prevent people from interrupting and speaking over each other. It also let quieter people jump into conversations easier.</p><p>As far as I can tell, <a href='http://zoom.us/'>Zoom</a> is still the winner in terms of video conferencing.</p><p>I also recommend using a headset with dedicated microphone for talking through your computer. The sound quality is usually better than using the built-in microphone.</p><h2>End</h2><p>It can be difficult to get good at working from home. It is definitely a skill that is learned through experience and reflection. If you have any questions about working remotely, feel free to reach out on <a href='https://twitter.com/jakemcc'>twitter</a> or through <a href='mailto:jake@jakemccrary.com'>email</a>.</p><p>Working from home can be a great experience. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>A desk can be any table that you can work on that is comfortable for a reasonable amount of time. It doesn't have to be what someone would typically think of as a desk.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-2'>I used a table like this for years in college and when working an internship.<a href='#fnref2'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-3'>These are also useful for in-person meetings.<a href='#fnref3'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-4'>No, not the middle finger.<a href='#fnref4'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/10/31/a-guide-to-distributed-work/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2017/10/31/a-guide-to-distributed-work/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[A guide to distributed work]]></title>
    <updated>2017-10-31T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>Whether it is working as the one remote employee at a traditional company or being one of many at a distributed company, remote work is becoming an option for many of us.</p><p>The number of employees that work remotely is growing<a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a>. Technology improvements, pervasive Internet, and mindset changes are some of the drivers for this change.</p><p>The remainder of this article highlights some observations from my last few years of working for distributed companies. I've also interviewed and corresponded with many other remote and formerly remote workers. Their contributions, along with books and articles on remote work, have influenced my thinking about what it means to have a successful distributed company. I've been working remotely since October 2013 in roles that have ranged from being a team lead to software developer to CTO. Each company I've worked for was fully distributed. There were no offices.</p><p>The types of distributed companies I've worked with have not been asynchronous. They have had core working hours centered around one of the middle time zones in the continental United States. You could work from anywhere, but you needed to be willing to work while others were working. I consider this synchronous remote work.</p><p>Much of the following also applies to individuals working remotely for a not-entirely-distributed company or team. Being the only remote individual in a non-remote team comes with its own set of challenges that I'm not going to attempt to present. If you are part of a team where some members work remotely, my recommendation is that you should treat that team as a remote team. If you don't, the remote worker will have a harder time keeping up with the rest of the team.</p><h2>Benefits</h2><p>If you ask someone that has never worked remotely before for the benefits of working remotely, they would probably be able to guess at some of the most obvious benefits. The top two responses I've received to this question are having no commute and more flexibility in your schedule. These two advantages are huge. There are other, less obvious advantages as well.</p><h3>No commute</h3><p>This is the benefit that most workers, remote and non-remote, identify when asked about benefits of remote work. This benefit stands out because it is huge and obvious. In the United States, the average one-way commute is <a href='https://project.wnyc.org/commute-times-us/embed.html#5.00/42.000/-89.500'>25 minutes long</a>. The average worker spends nearly one hour going to and from their work.</p><p>If you are going to work five days a week, then you're spending over four hours commuting.  That is half of a full workday riding a bicycle, car, train, or bus. In the best case scenario, you are using that time to read, listen to a podcast, or trying to think deeply about a problem. In reality, you're trying to do one of those activities, but you are continuously distracted by the world around you. You have to worry about avoiding accidents, driving safely, or another distracting concern.</p><p>Commuting has been shown to have negative effects on the commuters<a href='#fn-2' id='fnref2'><sup>2</sup></a>. Being able to work remotely lets you avoid those problems.</p><h3>Flexibility in schedule</h3><p>This is another benefit that most people can immediately identify. Remote works gives you more power over your schedule. Even if you're part of a synchronous distributed team, you gain flexibility. All of a sudden your breaks become time you can use to enrich your non-work life.</p><p>Picking up or dropping off your children at daycare or school becomes easier. Taking your dog for a midday walk becomes possible. Since you aren't commuting, you have more time to make breakfast for you and your family. You can run errands or go to your favorite neighborhood lunch spot during the day. These errands and restaurant trips are quicker since you're effectively doing them at off hours as most of your neighbors are working at their office.</p><h3>More time with family</h3><p>If you're working at home, then it becomes easy to see your family more. You can say hi to your kids when they get home from school. You have more time in the evening to spend with your baby before bedtime.</p><h3>Customize your workspace</h3><p>You get to choose where you work. For many, this will be in a home office. This is your space. You get to make it your own.</p><p>Do you like to work in a cave? Paint the walls a dark color, block out the windows and enjoy your cave-like experience. Do you prefer sunlight and plants? Work near a window and add houseplants to your space. Do you want an awesome sit-stand desk and chair? Buy <a href='/blog/2015/03/31/my-home-work-space/'>them</a>.</p><p>One of my former colleagues likes to walk on a treadmill while standing or, if sitting, he enjoyed having <a href='https://www.amazon.com/DeskCycle-Exercise-Pedal-Exerciser-White/dp/B00B1VDNQA'>pedals</a> under his desk. These are customizations he would have a hard time getting at most offices.</p><h3>Eat the food you want to eat</h3><p>Many of us have preferred diet (or a diet we're forced to follow). When you work from home, it is easier to eat food you know you should eat.</p><p>When you work from an office, you have a few food options. You can bring your food, go out to eat, or (if your employer offers it) eat food provided by your company. If you follow a restrictive diet, all of these options are more hassle than making your lunch at home every day.</p><p>Feel like eating food someone else has prepared? You can still do that while working from home.</p><h3>Fewer interruptions</h3><p>As a remote worker, you can choose your working location. This lets you select a spot with fewer distractions. You can pick an ideal location that helps you achieve a state of <a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology&#41;'>flow</a>.</p><p>Minimizing interruptions is one of the keys to accomplishing challenging tasks. After an interruption, it takes up to a half an hour to get back to your original task<a href='#fn-3' id='fnref3'><sup>3</sup></a>.</p><h3>Off-hours support</h3><p>This is a benefit I have not seen mentioned many other places. Off-hours support becomes much easier if you are working remotely. The actions you would take for an urgent alert at 1 AM are the same actions you would take at 1 PM.</p><p>When you get that 1 AM page you don't have to struggle to remember how you check production while at home; this is an activity you do on a regular basis. You know what you need to do. You don't have to remember how to VPN into your company's network; you do that every day.</p><p>No one likes getting woken up by a support call. At least this way you get to use your normal tools for solving problems.</p><h3>Recruiting</h3><p>Since you aren't limited to your locale, you can recruit from a much broader region. This means you can find the top talent for your company. This is huge.</p><p>Back in late 2013, it was quite challenging to find experienced Clojure programmers. Because <a href='https://outpace.com'>Outpace</a> is a distributed company, we were able to hire experts from across the entire United States. We would not have been able to recruit nearly as well if we were limited to a single location.</p><h3>Employee retention</h3><p>If your company supports remote work, then you remove an entire reason for an employee leaving. Sometimes, a person needs to move.  Working for a company that supports remote work allows them to move and not leave the company.</p><h3>Reduced office costs</h3><p>Having a distributed workforce can reduce office costs drastically. In a fully distributed company, it could reduce the cost to zero. Realistically, I'd expect the company I work for to provide computer hardware so there are still some costs<a href='#fn-4' id='fnref4'><sup>4</sup></a>. Unless the company pays for Internet and phone, the recurring costs are minimal.</p><h2>Downsides</h2><p>While there are many benefits, there are also downsides to working remotely. When I talk to non-remote workers about working remotely, I typically hear "I don't know how you do it, I'd be so distracted." This statement touches on one of the downsides of remote work, but it isn't largest one. Below are some downsides that I and others have observed.</p><h3>Loneliness and isolation</h3><p>Nearly everyone I've talked to, including myself, puts this as the top downside.</p><p>Most of us are social creatures. You do not get the same type of social interaction with your coworkers when you are working remotely. Instead of bumping into a wide range of people in the office, you interact with a smaller group through video chats, phone calls, chat rooms, and email. Depending on what you are doing, you might not even get that interaction.</p><p>This is very unfamiliar to most of us. We're used to being in physical proximity to other humans. We're used to having small talk and grabbing coffee or lunch with other people.</p><p>You can combat these feelings by setting up communication with other employees at your company. Have some dedicated chat rooms for non-work discussions. Have a daily, short video meeting that is a status check within the team so that everyone gets to see another person's face at least once a day. If you work in a city that has other remote workers from your company then meet up occasionally for dinner, lunch, or happy hour.</p><p>If you are having troubles with loneliness and isolation, try to find an area where you can work surrounded by other people. Two options are co-working spaces and coffee shops. Alternatively, try to have social activities you regularly do with non-coworkers in your area. Having strong connections with non-coworkers can help combat loneliness.</p><p>If I stay inside for more than a couple days, I get grumpy. I didn't realize this when I worked in an office. Noticing this has benefited my rock climbing, as I've made that my main non-work social activity. Even if I merely go bouldering by myself, being around other humans helps. If you're working remotely and feeling grumpy, try to find an activity you can regularly do and see if doing that helps.</p><h3>Distractions</h3><p>This is the downside that non-remote workers most often identify. People assume that television and other distractions in your home are irresistible and will cause you not to get work done. When you are working 100% remotely, you don't have the same distractions you have when you are only occasionally working remotely. You can't do laundry every day. You only have so much TV you can watch.</p><p>Personally, I don't have a problem with distractions when working at home. I know others that do. They mostly have when they first started working from home. When they first started working at home, they found themselves doing too much around the house. As a result, they worked late hours or felt like they weren't getting enough work done. Once you recognize the problem, it is possible to train yourself not to get distracted.</p><p>Roommates, kids, and family are another (sometimes welcome) distraction. You can combat interruptions from others by setting boundaries. Many of my coworkers have a rule that when their office door is closed, they are unavailable. I'll claim that coworkers interrupting you in an office are more distracting as the much rarer interruption from someone within your home.</p><p>Employees that work remotely are typically choosing to work remotely. Once they get used to working remotely, distractions stop being a problem. They know they need to produce quality work and will take steps to make sure they do.</p><h3>Working too much</h3><p>When you first start working from home, you suddenly find yourself living in the same space that you work. This lack of change in location and commute makes it easy to keep working. You get invested in a problem and all of a sudden it is past the time when you should have stopped working.</p><p>Even if you manage to stop working on time, it is easy to slip back into work mode. The computer setup I like to use in the evening is in the same location as my work setup. This makes it easy for me to take one more peek at our monitoring dashboards or check my work email.</p><p>You do not want to overwork and you do not want your teammates to overwork. In the short-term, overwork can be beneficial. Long-term it leads to burnout and poor outcomes.</p><h3>Fewer interactions</h3><p>This is a negative and positive. When you are working remotely, you have fewer random interactions with coworkers. You most likely interact with your team plus the same handful of people outside of your team regularly but you rarely interact with others.</p><p>In an office, there is a chance you'll run into people outside your usual circle of communication. You might eat lunch with a broader variety of people. You may bump into others while getting a coffee or a snack.</p><p>You can help increase interactions on a distributed team by having some chat rooms that encourage random discussions. Another option is to have a regular and optional meeting scheduled where people can give an informal presentation on something that interests them.</p><h2>Tools</h2><p>You will need to select tools that work for distributed teams. Most computer or web-based tools can work in a distributed setting. Any physical tools (such as pen and paper) will not work.</p><p>A prime example of this is the <a href='http://www.caroli.org/the-card-wall/'>classic card wall</a> for tracking work. A physical wall with actual cards will not work as soon as there is a single remote worker on a team. Instead of a physical wall, you'll need to using something like <a href='https://trello.com'>Trello</a>.</p><p>It is less important to get stuck on a particular tool recommendation and more essential to pay attention to the categories of tools. Categories of tools tend to be more stable than a specific recommendation.</p><h3>Text chat</h3><p>You'll want a chat application. <a href='https://slack.com'>Slack</a> and <a href='https://www.stride.com/'>Stride</a> are just two of the many available services.</p><h3>Video conference</h3><p>Video conferencing is a technology that you should embrace. It is much better than talking to either an individual or a group on the phone. Being able to read body language makes communication far better. Personally, I've used Google Hangouts and <a href='https://zoom.us'>Zoom</a> for hundreds of hours each and prefer Zoom. <a href='https://appear.in'>appear.in</a> is another option that doesn't require installing anything. There are many options in this space and more keep appearing. It is even built into Slack.</p><h3>Phone conferences</h3><p>I'd try to get rid of phone conferences in preference to video conferences. Video chat has many benefits over conference calls. I actually can't recommend any phone conferencing tools, but I will mention that Zoom supports people dialing into a video conference.</p><h3>Screen sharing</h3><p>You'll want to have a way to show another person or group what is on your screen. It is even better if someone else can take control of your machine or use their cursor to point towards something on your screen.</p><p>Most of my experience with this is using the feature built-in to Zoom. Pretty much every video conference tool I've used (appear.in, Google Hangouts, etc.) has screen sharing built-in.</p><h3>Real-time collaboration on a document</h3><p>Being able to collectively edit a document with a group is pretty amazing. <a href='http://etherpad.org/'>Etherpad</a> and <a href='https://www.google.com/intl/en/docs/about/'>Google Docs</a> are two options. Most of my experience is with Google Docs.</p><p>When a document supports real-time collaboration, you can do amazing things. You can use it to capture ideas from a remote group. An extreme version of this can be viewed by opening <a href='http://idlewords.com/talks/fan_is_a_tool_using_animal.htm'>this page</a> and searching for "Google doc."</p><p>You can use a shared document to facilitate a remote meeting (this goes incredibly well once you get the practice of it). Having a document that everyone in a meeting can edit is so much better than a whiteboard that only one or two people can simultaneously use.</p><h3>Whiteboards</h3><p>Whiteboards are an example of a tool that is always brought up, even by remote workers, as something that distributed teams miss. There are alternatives.</p><p>Whiteboards are a very convenient tool when meeting in-person, but there are other ways of collaborating when working remotely. Shared documents and screen sharing go a long way towards enabling collaboration. Tools that work well for remote collaboration often have another benefit over whiteboards; they are easier to persist and reference later.</p><p>One whiteboard alternative is Zoom's built-in whiteboard. It works fairly well. Another is to use <a href='https://drawings.google.com'>Google Drawings</a>. <a href='https://precursorapp.com/'>Precursor</a> is a design focused collaborative tool that can also work.</p><p>Even after four years, I occasionally find myself missing a whiteboard or shared piece of paper. Drawing with a mouse isn't ideal. I know some developers that use an iPad or a Wacom tablet to help them quickly sketch diagrams for their team.</p><h2>Communication</h2><p>Communication is inherently different on a distributed team. You cannot just walk across an office to interrupt someone and ask them a question. Communication happens mostly through text. You need to be skilled at written communication.</p><p>You lose context with written communication when compared to vocal or in-person communication. You no longer have body language or tone of voice to help you interpret what someone means. Lack of tone is huge. This is one reason that text communication is interpreted as more emotionally negative or neutral than intended<a href='#fn-5' id='fnref5'><sup>5</sup></a>. If you're reading text communication, try to read it with a positive tone.</p><p>It can also be useful to have rules around the expectations of different forms of communication. How quickly do you need to respond to an email? How quick should a response be to a chat room message?  When should you pick up the phone and call someone?</p><h3>Chat rooms</h3><p>Chat room applications (IRC, Slack, Stride, Flowdock, etc.) are pretty great. They provide a medium of communication that has a lower barrier to entry than email. Chat tools have a place in the distributed teams tool chest.</p><p>The chat room becomes even more central to work once you start including useful bots in the room. These bots can perform many functions. You can look in the <a href='https://slack.com/apps'>Slack App Directory</a> to see some of the bots that people are producing.</p><p>If you start adding bots and other automated messages to your chat application, you might want to think about setting up a separate channel. Some messages are not worthy of being interjected into your team's main chat. They can be distracting and hurt the flow of conversation. These messages tend to be ones that are informative, but not critical. For my teams, these messages include things like git commits and Trello card updates. It is great to see these in a single spot but annoying when they interrupt a conversation.</p><p>Chat rooms can also be a big time sink. They are a source of concentration interrupting notifications. The feeling of missing out on conversations can drive people to join a large number of channels. This piles on the potential for distraction.</p><p>Chat rooms also provide a feeling of immediacy that isn't actually there. You don't know if key people have seen your message or have had time to respond.</p><p>Despite having search functionality, I've found it hard to find previous conversations in chat applications. If something important appears in chat, I'd recommend extracting it from the chat application and recording it somewhere else.</p><p>I'd also recommend turning off notifications for all but most definite "someone is trying to reach me" triggers. Encourage members of your chat to use entire channel notifications sparingly and only for messages that need everyone's attention. There are not many messages that immediately require everyone's attention.</p><p>It can be a challenge to follow chat conversations, especially if they span a larger unit of time. Don't be afraid to move a conversation to email or another medium that is better suited for longer and more complex discussions.</p><p>Many chat applications offer the ability to have private rooms or to send direct messages to a user. Don't be afraid of using these private channels, but if your communication can be public, it should be public. It can be challenging to ask a question and admit you don't know something but seeing that dialogue might help others. Similarly, having discussions about a feature, bug, or task can help spread knowledge.</p><h3>Email</h3><p>Despite all of the efforts to replace email; email is still useful. It is the most common form of communication between companies, it is pervasive, and it usually comes with good search capabilities.</p><p>A good email thread can keep a topic contained in a form that is possible to follow. Unlike a chat room, there (usually) aren't off-topic interjections from uninvolved parties.</p><h3>Phone</h3><p>You shouldn't be afraid of calling someone. Just recognize that this is an interruption. Your company should have a directory of telephone numbers that is accessible to everyone.</p><p>One downside of any voice conversation is that it is not automatically persisted. It can be worth following up a phone call with an email summarizing the discussion and the next steps.</p><h3>Picking the right communication medium</h3><p>When you are working on a distributed team, you can no longer walk over to someone's desk and interrupt them. This is great. Not every question deserves an immediate answer.</p><p>Agree with your team when to use different forms of communication. Set expectations with regards to response times and urgency for different mediums. Maybe direct chat messages are expected to be responded to in under 10 minutes. Perhaps emails are OK having a delay of a few hours. This is something your group will need to decide.</p><h2>Practices</h2><p>These are some practices I've seen work well with distributed teams. Many of them are slight variations on what you might have experienced on a co-located team.</p><h3>Stand-ups</h3><p>Most of the teams I've been part of, whether distributed or co-located, have had a daily stand-up meeting. The intention of this meeting was to provide a short, scheduled time for communicating any roadblocks to progress, interesting information, status updates, and desire for help.</p><p>For a distributed stand-up, the team joins a video conference and we gather around a shared Google Doc that has prompts similar to the snippet below.</p><pre><code>Day: 2017-07-11

What's interesting?

Want help?

Meetings:
</code></pre><p>These prompts provide a starting point for team members to add additional text. Our stand-ups were at the beginning of the day, so frequently team members would add text to the document at the end of the prior day. Filling in the document at the end of the day instead of right before the stand-up was useful as memories and thoughts were often fresher without having to remember them the following morning.</p><p>After being filled in, the document would look like below.</p><pre><code>Day: 2017-07-11

What's interesting?
  - New deploy lowered response time by 20% &#91;Jake&#93;
  - Discovered bug in date-time library around checking if date is within interval &#91;Sue&#93;
  - Greg joined the team!
  - Adding blocker functionality going to take longer than expected &#91;Donald&#93;

Want help?
  - Having difficulties running batch process locally. &#91;Tom&#93;
  - I'm having a hard time understanding propensity calculation &#91;Mike&#93;

Meetings:
  - API overview with client @ 2 PM Central &#91;Jake/Jeremy&#93;
</code></pre><p>We would gather around the Google Doc and everyone would take a couple of minutes to read silently. If anyone felt like something was worth talking about they would <strong>bold</strong> the text and then we'd work from top to bottom and have a quick discussion. For our <code>Want help?</code> section we'd solicit volunteers and move on. The <code>Meetings</code> section was primarily there to provide visibility as to when certain members might not be available. After we worked through the <code>Want help?</code> section we'd pop over to Trello and review the work in progress and make sure everyone had an idea of what they would be doing that day.</p><p>The nice thing about doing a stand-up around a shared Google Doc is that you can put in richer media than just text. Screenshots of monitoring graphs were a regular addition to the <code>What's interesting?</code> section.</p><p>Every day a new section was added to the top of the Google Doc and the previous day was pushed lower on the page. Having this written history of stand-ups was useful as it allowed us to notice patterns through a persisted medium instead of relying on our memory. It also let someone who was on vacation come back and have an idea of what had happened while they were gone. Below is what the document would look like on the next day (comments removed to keep the example shorter).</p><pre><code>Day: 2017-07-12

What's interesting?
  - &#91;...&#93;

Want help?
  - &#91;...&#93;

Meetings:
  - &#91;...&#93;

-------
Day: 2017-07-11

What's interesting?
  - &#91;...&#93;

Want help?
  - &#91;...&#93;

Meetings:
  - &#91;...&#93;
</code></pre><p>Above is an example from one of the teams I led. Another team used the following prompts.</p><pre><code>1. Accomplished Yesterday

2. Requires Attention/Roadblocks

3. Scope Creep Alerts

4. Would like to Do Today
</code></pre><p>The important thing is to find something that works for your team. Different teams are going to prefer different formats.</p><p>Another interesting benefit of using a Google Doc to drive your stand-up is that it can be visible to other teams. You can even combine teams into a single document. Below is an example with two teams in a single document.</p><pre><code>&#42;&#42;Everyone&#42;&#42;
  - &#91;...&#93;

&#42;&#42;Team Events&#42;&#42;
  1. Accomplished Yesterday
     - &#91;...&#93;
  2. Requires Attention/Roadblocks
     - &#91;...&#93;
  3. Scope Creep Alerts
     - &#91;...&#93;
  4. Would like to do today
     - &#91;...&#93;

&#42;&#42;Team Engine&#42;&#42;
What's interesting?
  - &#91;...&#93;
Want help?
  - &#91;...&#93;
Meetings:
  - &#91;...&#93;
</code></pre><p>I've seen this work successfully with five related teams in a single document. News and information that affects everyone is added in the <code>Everyone</code> section. Team specific information is put in the team sections. Each team still has their individual stand-up where they only look at their section. But since their section is part of the larger document, they get a taste of what is going on in the other related teams. This helps replace the random hallway chatter you get in a shared office and gives everyone a slightly broader picture.</p><p>This worked shockingly well. I've had colleagues reach out, some years after leaving, to ask for the template we used for this multi-team stand-up.</p><h3>Stand-downs</h3><p>Stand-downs are a meeting that provides time to informally chat with a group. I've seen them used as an optional end-of-day water cooler activity for a group to talk about whatever. These chats often happen, but are unscheduled, in an office.</p><p>These meetings should be an optional, short meeting scheduled near the end of the day. This gives team members a good excuse (socializing with their coworkers) to stop working (which helps with the problem of overwork). No one should feel pressure to be at these meetings.</p><p>The conversation may or may not be work-related. Maybe you discuss a language feature someone learned. You might talk about a book you started reading. It doesn't matter what is discussed; these meetings can help a team get closer and promote more social interaction.</p><p>I've also worked with teams that play games, such as <a href='https://jackboxgames.com/project/jbpp3/'>Jackbox Party Packs</a>, through video conferences.</p><h3>Remote Pair Programming</h3><p><a href='http://c2.com/xp/PairProgramming.html'>Pair programming</a> is a technique that people often employ when working in-person. It works even better when remote and helps solve some of the difficulties of working remotely.</p><p>Remote pair programming helps fight the feeling of loneliness and isolation that remote workers feel. Remote pairing forces intense interaction between two people. It also helps keep the two people focused on work. It is easy for a single person to get distracted by browsing Hacker News but much harder for both people to get sucked into it.</p><p>The ideal in-person pair programming setup is when you take a single computer and hook up two large monitors, two keyboards, and two mice and then mirror the monitors. This lets both programmers use their personal keyboard and stare straight ahead at their monitor.</p><p>Remote pair programming is an even better setup. One developer, the host, somehow shares their environment with the other developer. This can be done through screen sharing using Zoom, Slack, VNC, tmate, or some other way. The important part is that both developers can see the code and, if necessary, someway of viewing a UI component. They should both be able to edit the code.</p><p>Like the ideal local pair programming environment, each developer uses their personal keyboard, mouse, and monitor. Unlike the local pair programming environment, they each also have their own computer. This lets one developer look up documentation on their computer while the host developer continues to write code. It also allows the non-host developer to shield the host from distractions like answering questions in the chat room or responding to emails.</p><p>When remote programming it is easier for the non-host developer to stop paying attention. It is easier to be rude and not pay attention to your pair when you are not sitting next to them. If you notice your pair has zoned out, nicely call them out on it or ask them a question to get them to re-engage.</p><h3>One-on-ones</h3><p>One-on-ones are a useful practice in both a co-located and distributed team. For those who aren't familiar with one-on-ones, they are meetings between you and your manager (flip that if you are the manager). They should be scheduled regularly and be a time where you discuss higher-level topics than the daily work. They are extremely useful for helping you develop professionally and helping a team run smoothly. If you currently have one-on-ones and you aren't finding them useful, I'd recommend reading some articles with tips for making them useful. Here are a <a href='https://www.themuse.com/advice/how-to-have-oneonones-that-actually-matter'>couple</a> <a href='https://hbr.org/2016/08/how-to-make-your-one-on-ones-with-employees-more-productive'>articles</a> that give some pretty good advice. As both a team lead and a team member I've found one-on-ones extremely useful. I thought they were even more useful when on a distributed team.</p><p>With a distributed team you lose out on a lot of the body language you can pick up on when in person. It is harder to tell when someone is frustrated or when a pair is not working well together. Burnout is harder to notice. One-on-ones provide a time for that information to come out.</p><h3>Meet in person</h3><p>You should have your distributed team or company meet in person. This shouldn't happen too regularly; I think this ideally happens two to four times a year. Even if you see someone every day on video, there is still some magic that happens when you meet in person<a href='#fn-6' id='fnref6'><sup>6</sup></a>.</p><p>You can use this time to do the typical day-to-day work, but I think it is more productive to try other activities. The most successful in-person meetups I've been part of consisted mostly of group discussions. This can take the form of a mini-conference or <a href='http://openspaceworld.org/wp2/what-is/'>Open Space</a>. Another option is to brainstorm some potentially wild ideas and try implementing them to see how far you can get.</p><p>Use this time to have some meals and drinks with your coworkers. Play some board games and talk about things other than work. Sing some karaoke. Get to know your coworkers as more than someone inside your computer. Doing so can help with communication and understanding personalities.</p><h2>End</h2><p>It is an exciting time to be a remote worker. New tools are emerging that try to make remote work easier. New techniques are being discovered. Old techniques are being adapted.</p><p>I hope you've found this article useful. If you are a remote worker, maybe you've picked up some ideas to bring into your remote work. If you work in an office, perhaps you've found some useful arguments for moving towards remote work. </p><p>There is much more I could write about remote work and distributed teams. Some of these sections deserve their own posts and extended examples. You can view the <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>remote category</a> of my site to view other articles I've already written.</p><p>If you've enjoyed this article, consider sharing (<a href='https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=A%20guide%20to%20distributed%20work%20https%3A%2F%2Fjakemccrary.com%2Fblog%2F2017%2F10%2F31%2Fa-guide-to-distributed-work%2F&via=jakemcc'>tweeting</a>) it to your followers.</p><h2>Acknowledgments</h2><p>This article came to life from the notes and research I did prior to speaking at the <a href='http://lanyrd.com/2016/aitworkshop/'>2016 AIT Workshop</a>. Some of those notes came from correspondence with <a href='https://timothypratley.blogspot.com/'>Timothy Pratley</a>, <a href='http://www.rustybentley.com/'>Rusty Bentley</a>, <a href='http://gigasquidsoftware.com/'>Carin Meier</a>, <a href='https://twitter.com/devn'>Devin Walters</a>, <a href='https://twitter.com/kidpollo'>Paco Viramontes</a>, <a href='http://www.xpteam.com/'>Jeff Bay</a>, and <a href='http://www.grayduckllc.com/'>Michael Halvorson</a>. Discussions at the conference, with the above individuals, and working remotely at <a href='https://outpace.com'>Outpace</a> and <a href='https://lumanu.com'>Lumanu</a> really helped solidify my thoughts.</p><h2>Other references</h2><ul><li><a href='https://www.amazon.com/Remote-Office-Required-Jason-Fried/dp/0804137501'>Remote - Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</a></li><li><a href='https://zapier.com/learn/the-ultimate-guide-to-remote-working/'>The Ultimate Guide to Remote Work - Zapier</a></li><li><a href='http://paul.stadig.name/2013/07/remote-distributed.html'>Remote != Distributed - Paul Stadig</a></li><li><a href='http://bob.mcwhirter.org/blog/2010/09/13/remote-worker-distributed-team/'>Remote worker vs distributed team - Bob Mcwhirter</a></li><li><a href='http://martinfowler.com/articles/remote-or-co-located.html'>Remote or co-located - Martin Fowler</a></li></ul><ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'><a href='http://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/telecommuting-statistics'>http://globalworkplaceanalytics.com/telecommuting-statistics</a><a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-2'>Various articles: <a href='https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/urban-survival/201501/commuting-the-stress-doesnt-pay'>one</a>, <a href='http://time.com/9912/10-things-your-commute-does-to-your-body/'>two</a>, <a href='http://www.businessinsider.com/long-commutes-have-an-impact-on-health-and-productivity-2017-5'>three</a>, <a href='https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2014/feb/12/how-does-commuting-affect-wellbeing'>four</a>, <a href='http://www.npr.org/2011/10/19/141514467/small-changes-can-help-you-thrive-happily'>five</a>, <a href='https://www.forbes.com/sites/amymorin/2014/12/07/want-to-be-happier-change-your-commute-or-change-your-attitude/#5d71cadc7417'>six</a>, <a href='http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20160107224314/http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/dcp171766_351954.pdf'>seven</a><a href='#fnref2'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-3'><a href='http://www.npr.org/2015/09/22/442582422/the-cost-of-interruptions-they-waste-more-time-than-you-think'>http://www.npr.org/2015/09/22/442582422/the-cost-of-interruptions-they-waste-more-time-than-you-think</a><a href='#fnref3'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-4'>Though, you may want to pay for the Internet or provide a budget to help remote employees set up their home office.<a href='#fnref4'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-5'><a href='http://amr.aom.org/content/33/2/309.short'>Carrying too Heavy a Load? The Communication and Miscommunication of Emotion by Email</a> and <a href='https://www.fastcodesign.com/3036748/evidence/why-its-so-hard-to-detect-emotion-in-emails-and-texts'>Why It's So Hard To Detect Emotion In Emails And Texts</a><a href='#fnref5'>&#8617;</a></li><li id='fn-6'>Like being surprised at how tall or short your coworkers are. It gets me every time.<a href='#fnref6'>&#8617;</a></li></ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/28/seven-tips-for-successful-remote-meetings/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[7 tips for a successful remote meeting]]></title>
    <updated>2016-06-28T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>As mentioned in my <a href='/blog/2016/06/14/tips-for-working-from-home/'>tips for working from home</a> article, I've been working remotely for nearly three years. In those three years I've been in countless meetings, both productive and unproductive. Meetings, both in-person and remote, are hard. Remote meetings pose some additional challenges but they also offer some unique benefits.</p><p>Below are seven tips that will help you have successful remote meetings. I wrote this article focusing on remote meetings but many of these tips will improve your co-located meetings as well.</p><h3>Have an agenda</h3><p>If you are organizing a meeting, you should make sure that the meeting has an agenda. The agenda doesn't have to be a long, complicated document; it can be as simple as a list of topics and goals.</p><p>Why should you have an agenda? An agenda helps focus discussion by providing an outline of what the meeting is designed to cover.</p><p>Send out your agenda with the meeting invite. This gives invitees time to think about the topics and helps prevent people from showing up clueless. It also provides an opportunity for an invitee to excuse themself or suggest an alternative person if they don't believe they will contribute to the meeting.</p><h3>Start and end on time</h3><p>You should start your meetings on time. You should end your meetings on time or early. If you are not starting and ending on time then you are not being respectful of your attendees time. The lack of punctuality contributes towards people dreading meetings.</p><p>If you are running out of time, wind down the meeting. If more discussions need to happen, reflect and see if more time needs to be scheduled with the entire group or if only a subset of the group is required.</p><h3>Use video chat</h3><p>Even if you don't work remotely, you've probably had to dial in to a group audio chat. This is almost always a terrible experience. Without body language, it is near impossible to tell when someone is about to start speaking and, as a result, there are awkward pauses while everyone waits for someone else to speak and everyone speaks over each other. It is terrible.</p><p>This is why I recommend using video chat. Video chats let you see the other people on the call and this allows you to pick up on physical cues. These cues vastly improve communication in the meeting.</p><h3>Co-located attendees should use their own device</h3><p>Sometimes you'll have a mixed meeting, some attendees are remote and others are together in an office. The co-located attendees should each use their own device to connect to the meeting.</p><p>Co-located attendees sharing a single device is non-optimal for many reasons. It is often hard for all the co-located attendees to be captured by the camera in a way that enables the remote attendees to reliably view them. Sharing a single microphone also makes it so some co-located attendees are easy to hear and others are barely audible.</p><p>Using a single device also makes it harder for all the co-located attendees to view the remote attendees. Without a clear view of the remote attendees, the co-located attendees often accidentally exclude the remote people by focusing on discussions between the co-located group.</p><h3>Ignore distractions</h3><p>Hopefully you have invited just the right people to the meeting and everyone is engaged in the discussion and paying attention. Realistically this doesn't happen. Computers are incredibly good at so many things and one of those things is distracting the user.</p><p>When you are attending a remote meeting, minimize what can distract you. Close your email and hide the chat program. Put your phone out of arms reach. Try to focus intently on the meeting. If you find yourself not paying attention and not contributing, take this as a signal that you shouldn't be in this meeting. If nothing on the rest of the agenda seems like it requires you, then leave the meeting and be more selective about what you join in the future.</p><p>If you notice other attendees not paying attention, gently call them out on it. This can be done by soliciting discussion from them or by being direct.  </p><h3>Have a shared artifact</h3><p>This is one of the more important tips in this list and it is one of the areas where remote meetings have an advantage over in-person meetings.</p><p>When the meeting starts give everyone a link to a shared document that everyone can edit (for example a <a href='https://www.google.com/docs/about/'>Google Doc</a>). It can be useful to seed this document with the agenda. This shared document can be used to capture whatever you want. I've found it useful to capture options discussed, pros/cons lists, and follow-up actions. Writing in the shared document helps solidify ideas and gives the group a reference both during and after the meeting.</p><p>With in-person meetings, this shared artifact is often a whiteboard. Whiteboards are immensely useful but are barely editable by more than one person at once and are harder to reference after a meeting. I know I'm not the only person who dislikes trying to decipher terrible whiteboard handwriting captured by someone's phone.</p><p>Except for when drawing diagrams, I've found the Google Docs style shared document used during a remote meeting more effective than using a whiteboard in an in-person meeting. You can always use a shared document in an in-person meeting as well but then you are requiring attendees to have a laptop open and that is an invitation for distracted attendees.</p><h3>Assign responsibilities</h3><p>Hopefully you are having a meeting to influence an outcome and not just hear everyone talk. As a result, you should be assigning follow-up responsibilities as the meeting progresses. Make the follow-up actions explicit and assigned to an individual. You can capture these responsibilities in your shared artifact.<h2></h2></p><p>Meetings can be difficult. You should do what you can to make them more successful. If you are being invited to a meeting without an agenda, ask for an agenda. If you're in a meeting and you can tell someone is constantly distracted, try nicely calling them out on it (either privately or in the group). If there isn't a shared artifact, make one and suggest it to the group. Meetings don't have to be terrible. We can make them better.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/14/tips-for-working-from-home/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2016/06/14/tips-for-working-from-home/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Tips for working from home]]></title>
    <updated>2016-06-14T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>I've been working remotely since October 2013. I can barely believe that nearly three years have passed and I've probably spent about two weeks in a traditional office.</p><p>It took me a bit of time to adjust to working remotely. I'm better at it now than I was three years ago. The rest of this post describes some of my learnings.</p><p>But first, some background. My remote experience comes from working at <a href='http://outpace.com'>Outpace</a> and <a href='https://lumanu.com'>Lumanu</a>. Both are remote first companies, almost everyone works remotely with a few people occasionally working in a San Francisco office. The work is remote but it is not asynchronous. Both companies value pair programming and real time collaboration and, as a result, employees tend to work a core set of hours. My observations are probably most applicable in a similar environment.</p><h3>Setup a home workspace</h3><p>Before working remotely I did not have a great home computing setup. I worked using a 13-inch MacBook Air either sitting on my couch or at my dinner table. This worked fine for the occasional work-from-home day and for evening and weekend programming. It didn't work fine when I was spending extended hours at a computer every day.</p><p>I've written about my setup <a href='/blog/2015/03/31/my-home-work-space/'>before</a>. Below is a list of the improvements I made to my home working environment.</p><ol><li>Outpace provided a beefy MacBook Pro and two 27-inch Apple Cinema displays.</li><li>I upgraded my chair to to a <a href='https://www.amazon.com/Setu-Chair-Herman-Miller-Standard/dp/B004VSL6E6'>Herman Miller Setu</a>.</li><li>I bought a <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000OOYECC/'>mStand Laptop Stand</a> to raise my laptop to a better viewing height.</li><li>I upgraded my desk to a sit-stand desk.</li><li>I built my own <a href='/blog/2014/07/27/building-the-ergodox-keyboard/'>ErgoDox keyboard</a>.</li><li>I switched to an adjustable monitor arm so I could adjust my monitor height.</li></ol><p>With each change my working experience improved. Each improvement left me feeling better at the end of my day. Many, if not all, of these improvements are things I'd expect to have in a traditional office. Don't skimp on your setup because it is in your home. Part of your home is your office now.</p><h3>Introduce a habit that delineates work from after-work</h3><p>One of the great things about working from home is that you no longer have a commute. You don't have to dodge cars on your bicycle, squeeze into a train, or sit in traffic while driving. This is a huge benefit.</p><p>A downside of not having a commute is that you lose a forced intermission between work and non-work. My commute was either a 30-minute bicycle ride or a 30-minute public transit ride. That time acted as a forced decompression period where I focused on something that wasn't computing.</p><p>It took me months to realize that not having this intermission was stressing me out. The intermission helped me shift between working and non-working mindsets.</p><p>I reintroduced a decompression activity between work and non-work and became less stressed and generally happier. I've replaced my commute intermission with reading, cooking, or riding my bicycle. I've found doing a non-computer activity benefits me the most.</p><h3>Stop working</h3><p>When I first started working from home I was very guilty of overworking. It was so easy to just keep working. I would get invested in a problem and all sudden realize it was time to go to bed. Or I'd actually stop working, only to find myself checking our application's monitoring or pulling up the codebase when I originally sat down to do some personal task.</p><p>In an office you have signals; your coworkers leaving, the cleaning crew vacuuming, air conditioning turning off, etc., that provide a hint that you should think about stopping. You don't have these signals when you are working remotely. There also isn't that spatial boundary between your office and your home.</p><p>You can search online and find many articles about how overwork is detrimental. You and your employer benefit if you are <strong>not</strong> overworked.</p><h3>Get out of your house</h3><p>I live in Chicago. During the winter the weather is very cold. Chicago is also a big city, so all sorts of food delivery options (both cooked and uncooked) exist. The cold weather combined with food delivery makes it easy to stay inside. During the winter, I've realized many times that I haven't left my apartment for days. My girlfriend can tell when I haven't gotten outside because I'm grumpier.</p><p>If I get out of the apartment for a while I almost always come back feeling better. It barely matters what I do when I leave, after an extended period of time inside of my home just getting outside and doing anything helps. A change of scenery is good for you.</p><h3>Don't just talk about business with your remote coworkers</h3><p>When you work in an office you are pretty much forced to have non-work related chats with coworkers. You should do the same with your remote team.</p><p>Having non-work related conversations helps you make better connections with your coworkers. These better connections can lead to better communication, both with voice and text, and humanize the person on the other side of the screen.</p><p>Its even better if you can do this in a video conference. Then you get to learn the facial expressions and tone of voice of your coworker. This can make it easier to interpret text communication in the way they actually mean it.</p><h3>Meet in person occasionally</h3><p>It is great that technology and Internet speeds have progressed enough that working remotely works well. If you want, you can make it feel like your pair is sitting right next to you. This is great.</p><p>There are still benefits to meeting in person though. The main one is that it helps you make connections with coworkers. You can eat a meal together or play board games (though, you can do this online as well but it is a different experience). It can also be easier to have certain types of group discussions (video conferences do have limitations).</p><p>When you meet in person, I'd recommend doing something different than your normal day-to-day work. Don't just exchange remote pairing for local pairing. Try to identify that are difficult to do remotely and do them in person.</p><p>I don't have a concrete recommendation for how often your remote company should meet but I think it should be infrequent enough where you don't feel pressure to do normal work.</p><h2>End</h2><p>Working from home has its challenges but with those challenges come many benefits. It is a different experience than working in an office and that experience isn't for everyone. The above recommendations are things that have helped me adjust to working remotely. Some of these tips are actionable at an individual level and some require buy in from the company. Hopefully this list can help give guidance towards improving your remote work situation.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/24/remote-pairing/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2015/01/24/remote-pairing/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[Remote Pairing]]></title>
    <updated>2015-01-24T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p>Over a year ago I joined <a href='http://outpace.com'>Outpace</a>. All of Outpace's developers are remote but we still practice pair programming. As a result I've done a lot of remote pairing. I was skeptical before joining that it would work well and I'm happy to report that I was wrong. Remote pairing works.</p><h2>Why remote pairing?</h2><p>The usual pair programming <a href='http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?PairProgrammingBenefits'>benefits</a> apply to remote pairing; more people know the code, quality is higher, and it provides an opportunity for mentorship. Another benefit, more beneficial in a remote setting, is that it increases **social interaction**.</p><p>The most common response I receive when I tell someone I work from my apartment is "I'd miss the interaction with co-workers." When you work remote you do miss out on the usual in office interaction. Pair programming helps replace some of this. It helps you build and maintain relationships with your remote colleagues.</p><h2>Communication</h2><p>Communication is an important part of pair programming. When you're pairing in person you use both physical and vocal communication. When remote pairing you primarily use vocal communication. You can pick up on some physical cues with video chat but it is hard. You will never notice your pair reaching for their keyboard.</p><p>I've used Google Hangouts, <a href='http://zoom.us'>Zoom</a>, and Skype for communication. Currently I'm primarily using Zoom. It offers high quality video and audio and usually doesn't consume too many resources.</p><p>I recommend not using your computers built-in microphone. You should use headphones with a mic or a directional microphone. You'll sound better and you'll stop your pair from hearing themselves through your computer.</p><p>I use <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005VAORH6'>these headphones</a>. They are cheap, light, and open-eared but are wired. I've been told I sound the best when I'm using them. I also own these <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003VANOFY'>wireless headphones</a>. They are closed-ear, heavier, and wireless. The wireless is great but the closed-ear design causes me to talk differently and by the end of the day my throat is hoarse. Both of these headphones are widely used by my colleagues and I don't think you can go wrong with either one.</p><p>Some people don't like wearing headphones all day. If you are one of those I'd recommend picking up a directional microphone. Many of my colleagues use a <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002OO333Q'>Snowball</a>.</p><h2>Connecting the machines</h2><p>So now you can communicate with your pair. It is time to deal with the main problem in remote pairing. How do you actually work on the same code with someone across the world?</p><p>At Outpace we've somewhat cheated and have standardized our development hardware. Everyone has a computer running OS X and, if they want it, at least one 27 inch monitor (mostly Apple 27 inch displays or a <a href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B009H0XQQY'>Dell</a>) with a resolution of 2560x1440. Since everyone has nearly identical hardware and software we are able to pair using OS X's built-in screen sharing. This allows full sharing of the host's desktop. This full desktop sharing is the best way to emulate working physically next to your pair. This enable the use of any editor and lets you both look at the same browser windows (useful for testing UIs or reading reference material). With decent internet connections both programmers can write code with minimal lag. This is my preferred way of pairing.</p><p>Another option that works well is <a href='http://tmate.io/'>tmate</a>. tmate is a fork of tmux that makes remote pairing easy. It makes it dead simple to have remote developer connect to your machine and share your terminal. This means you are stuck using tools that work in a terminal and, if you are working on a user interface, you need to share that some other way. There generally is less lag when the remote developer is typing.</p><p>A third option is to have the host programmer share their screen using screen sharing built-in to Google Hangouts or <a href='http://zoom.us'>Zoom</a>. This is a quick way to share a screen and is my preferred way of sharing GUIs with more than one other person. With both Zoom and Google Hangouts the remote developer can control the host's machine but it isn't a great experience. If you are pairing this way the remote developer rarely touches the keyboard.</p><h2>Soloing</h2><p>It might seem weird to have a section on soloing in an article about remote pairing. Soloing happens and even in an environment that almost entirely pairs it is important. Not everyone can or wants to pair 100% of the time. Soloing can be recharging. It is important to be self-aware and recognize if you need solo time. Below are a few tips for getting that solo time.</p><p>One way to introduce solo time is to take your lunch at a different time than your pair. This provides both of you and your pair with an opportunity to do a bit of soloing.</p><p>Other short soloing opportunities happen because of meetings and interviews. It isn't uncommon for half of a pair to leave for a bit to join a meeting, give an interview, or jump over to help out another developer for a bit.</p><p>Soloing also happens as a result of uneven team numbers. If your team is odd numbered than there are plenty of opportunities for being a solo developer. Try to volunteer to be the solo developer but be aware of becoming too isolated.</p><h2>Conclusion</h2><p>Remote pairing works. Working at <a href='http://outpace.com'>Outpace</a> has shown me how well it can work. Reasonably fast Internet paired with modern tools can make it seem like you're almost in the same room as your pair.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2014/12/09/an-effective-code-review-process/index.html</id>
    <link href="https://jakemccrary.com/blog/2014/12/09/an-effective-code-review-process/index.html"/>
    <title><![CDATA[An Effective Code Review Process]]></title>
    <updated>2014-12-09T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p> See all of my remote/working-from-home <a href='/blog/categories/remote/'>articles here</a>. </p></blockquote><p><a href='https://twitter.com/searls/status/540603801955471360'><img src="/images/justin-searls-code-reviews-harmful.png" alt="The way most organizations implement code reviews in teams is usually more harmful than helpful. I generally recommend going without them. - Justin Searls" title= "The way most organizations implement code reviews in teams is usually more harmful than helpful. I generally recommend going without them. - Justin Searls" /></a></p><p>The above was tweeted<a href='#fn-1' id='fnref1'><sup>1</sup></a> recently and it resulted in some decent discussion about code reviews. In the past six months at <a href='http://www.outpace.com'>Outpace</a>, I've been part of a handful of code review sessions that have been extremely productive. After the reviews many developers have expressed shock at the effectiveness of the process. A tweet-sized overview of the process we've followed can be found in <a href='https://twitter.com/gigasquid'>Carin Meier</a>'s <a href='https://twitter.com/gigasquid/status/540606002547425281'>responses</a> to the above tweet. Since you can't fit details into tweets the rest of this post expands on our code review process.</p><p>Some background before we dive into the details. <a href='http://www.outpace.com'>Outpace</a> is a software company that practices, despite every programmer working remotely, nearly 100% pair programming. In addition, the team Carin and I are on do most of our work through GitHub pull requests. Before merging with master, the pull requests are reviewed by other teammates. Between pairing and pull requests many eyes see every line of code as changes are made.</p><p>Even with all this, we've found value in having more traditional code reviews. We've found that different feedback and action items emerge from reviewing code that we already have than from reviews of code changes (e.g., pull requests).</p><p>In addition to working for the team described above, the process below has been successfully used to review an internal library where the reviewers where mostly interested users with a couple contributors. It has also been successful on teams that were not adherent to doing work through reviewed pull requests.</p><h3>The Code Review Process</h3><h4>Step 1: Select the code to review</h4><p>Typically we do this between a week and two weeks before the code review. Here we identify the code we want to review and create a two-hour meeting on a Friday at the end of day.</p><p>Having the meeting late on Friday helps create a relaxed environment. The review becomes a time to unwind, enjoy a beverage of choice, and talk about code. I haven't met a developer that doesn't enjoy discussing how to make code better and this lets everyone finish the week doing just that. The code review becomes an uplifting way to finish a week.</p><h4>Step 2: Open the code review</h4><p>A few days (typically late Tuesday or early Wednesday) before the Friday code review meeting we start the review. We do this by opening a <a href='https://github.com'>GitHub</a> pull request. The following steps will create a pull request where you can comment every line of code being reviewed.</p><ol><li>Create a local branch.</li><li>Delete the code being reviewed and commit locally.</li><li>Push the branch to GitHub.</li><li>Open a pull request.</li></ol><p>These steps are necessary because GitHub pull requests only let you view code that has changed. This process marks every line as deleted, which causes every line to appear the <i>Files changed</i> tab.</p><p>Opening the pull request a few days before the review meeting provides a location for pre-meeting comments to be added. This lets reviewers spend a couple days thinking about and commenting on the code. Comments on the pull request indicate a conversation should happen during the code review meeting.</p><h4>Step 3: The code review meeting</h4><p>Its finally Friday and time to review the code as a group. Everyone joins a video conference and someone volunteers to lead the code review. At least one other person volunteers to be a note taker.</p><p>The leader directs the code review and keeps it moving forward. To do this the leader shares their screen with the video conference and scrolls through the <i>Files changed</i> view of the pull request. When a comment appears on screen the leader stops scrolling and discussion starts.</p><p>The comments are read (often silently) and discussion happens. The leader tries to recognize when a conclusion has been reached or when further discussion, outside of the code review, needs to happen. When a conclusion is reached someone (often the leader) states a quick summary and a note taker records the next steps. The next steps are added as additional comments in the comment thread being discussed. As the next steps are recorded the leader moves on to the next comment.</p><p>This continues until either time runs out or the group runs out of things to discuss.</p><p>After the code review a volunteer turns the next steps comments into Trello cards and we take care of the code review items as part of our usual work.</p><h3>Results</h3><p>We've seen impressive improvements to code quality in the projects that have undergone this style of code review. Both small and large changes have happened as a result. Code has become simpler, clearer, and better understood. Additionally, the feeling of collective code ownership has increased.</p><p>Teammates have been surprised at how well this process has worked. More than a couple have said that historically they have not found code reviews useful but that these were.</p><p>This style of code review has worked in a few different settings and I encourage you to give it a shot. <ol class='footnotes'><li id='fn-1'>Reading through the discussion on Twitter after this tweet can give some hints as to what it takes to have an effective code review.<a href='#fnref1'>&#8617;</a></li></ol></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
